<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of Count Ulfeld, great master of Denmark, and of the Countess Eleonora his wife done out of French ; with a supplement thereunto, and to the account of Denmark formerly published.</title>
            <title>Comte d'Ulfeld, grand maistre de Danemarc. English</title>
            <author>Rousseau de la Valette, Michel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13530871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13530871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 800:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of Count Ulfeld, great master of Denmark, and of the Countess Eleonora his wife done out of French ; with a supplement thereunto, and to the account of Denmark formerly published.</title>
                  <title>Comte d'Ulfeld, grand maistre de Danemarc. English</title>
                  <author>Rousseau de la Valette, Michel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii, 139 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.] ,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rosseau de La Valette.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Comte d'Ulfeld, grand maistre de Danemarc.</note>
                  <note>First edition in English.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ulfeldt, Corfitz, --  greve, 1606-1664.</term>
               <term>Ulfeldt, Leonora Christina, --  grevinde, 1621-1698.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99996:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF Count <hi>ULFELD,</hi> GREAT MASTER of DENMARK, And of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> his Wife: Done out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A Supplement thereunto, and to the Account of <hi>Denmark</hi> former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99996:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:99996:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Duke of <hi>MONT A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SIER</hi> Governour to the DAUPHIN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO many Books have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been dedicated to you, and their Authors have ſo far ingroſs'd all manner of Thoughts, in endeavouring to give us a perfect Idea of
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:99996:3"/>your Vertues, that I want words to add new Praiſes to thoſe they have already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you. And indeed, my Lord, where ſhould I find proper words to expreſs the Confidence and Eſteem which the greateſt and wiſeſt of our Kings has repos'd in and demonſtrated towards you, in committing the Care of the <hi>Dauphin</hi>'s Education to you? This great Choice, puts your Merit ſo far above Praiſe and Envy, that there needs no other Elogy to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy Poſterity that you are a Man without Defects.
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:99996:3"/>Therefore, my Lord, I am perſwaded that a reſpectful Silence will prove more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, than all what I could ſay, and that in dedicating my Book to you, I ſhall offer you nothing that is worthy of you.</p>
            <p>If after this ſincere Avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, you will be pleas'd to honour it with your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it will be free from the Cenſure of thoſe Criticks who never like any thing; and I will think my ſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy, to have found this occaſion, to let the World
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:99996:4"/>know, that I am with all the Zeal and all the Reſpect ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed> Your moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant,
<hi>Rouſſeau de la Valette.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:99996:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THERE are ſtill ſo many Perſons at Court who have known Count <hi>Ulfeld,</hi> and his Retreat into <hi>Sweden</hi> made ſo much noiſe in the World, that every body will be pleas'd to hear the Hiſtory of his Life, and to know the motives which induc'd him to make War againſt his Country.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding you may find very ſurpriſing things in this Story, I can aſſure you that whatever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in it is certainly true; and that I have vritten nothing but what I have found in the <hi>Memoirs</hi> which were ſent to me out of <hi>Denmark,</hi> by unbyaſs'd
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:99996:5"/>knowing Perſons, without whom I could not have related many ſingular things, which were never written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>But whereas the matter I am treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of is conſiderable enough of it ſelf to be receiv'd kindly by the Publick; I will not trouble you with a long Preface: provided only you will be pleas'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my want of Capacity, I will think my ſelf ſufficiently rewarded for the pains I have taken in writing this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the reading of which is as curious as it may be uſeful.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99996:5"/>
            <head>The LIFE of CORNIFIX, COUNT of ULFELD, Great Maſter of DENMARK: And of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> his Wife.</head>
            <p>THE Perſons whoſe Lives I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to write, have ſhown ſo much Magnanimity in the different Turns of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that it is difficult to judg which they are moſt to be prais'd for, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration they have us'd in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, or the Conſtancy they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in their Diſtreſſes: but whatever State we conſider them in, their Elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and their Fall are equally Inſtructive; to learn never to rely on the Luſtre of a great Favour, and to ſuffer the utmoſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99996:6"/>Rigors of Fortune, without betraying the leaſt Weakneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornifix,</hi> Count of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> was the Tenth Son of Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Denmark;</hi> who in the Reign of King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as Illuſtrious by his Merit, as he was by his high Birth; his Family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the Firſt and moſt Antient of the Kingdom, and the only One that was honour'd with the Dignity of <hi>Count,</hi> by Conceſſion from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Beſides the Advantages which <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifix</hi> deriv'd from the Luſtre of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and from his Father's Favour, who rul'd the State, Nature prov'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry favourable to him, for he was the fineſt Gentleman of his Time; he had a Noble eaſy Shape, and a Majeſtick Air; his Mind was great and capable of all Things, his Eloquence was beyond the reach of moſt Men of his Quality; his Judgment was ſolid; he had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage without Oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; a great deal of Sweetneſs mix'd with Gravity, which procur'd him Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Good-Will from all Men; he was Faithful and Moderate, very Sober, Generous and Vigilant: In a Word, he would have been perfect, had he not been Ambitious.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99996:6"/>
            <p>Before he was ten Years of Age, the great Vivacity of his Mind made him commit ſo many youthful Frolicks, that his Father was oblig'd to ſend him to <hi>Paris,</hi> under the Tuition of a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; in order, if poſſible, to curb him by a Change of Clime: but on the contrary, his Malice increaſing with his Years, he became ſo rebellious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Governour, that after having endeavour'd in vain, for five Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to alter his Temper, he was forc'd at laſt to acquaint his Father the Chancellor with it; who was ſo angry thereat, that he order'd him to forſake him abſolutely, and to allow him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Cornifix</hi> finding himſelf thus at Liberty, tho he was but fifteen Years of Age, went into <hi>Germany,</hi> where he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himſelf to the Count of <hi>Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> to whom he had the Honour to be Related, and diſcover'd the Cauſe of his Diſgrace to him. As he was incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably well ſhap'd, and had a great deal of Wit, he ſoon became his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. And during the three Years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode he made at his Court, he became ſo accompliſh'd, that many Husbands became jealous of him. But his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Temper inſpiring him with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99996:7"/>of War above all other Things; Count <hi>Oldenburg</hi> could not hinder him from ingaging himſelf in King <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>'s Army, who was in actual War with ſome of the Princes of <hi>Germany:</hi> The ſaid Count having given him a magnificent Equipage, with Letters of Recommendation to General <hi>Fowlk,</hi> one of the greateſt Captains of his Time, he took his leave of him, with as much Regret as Tenderneſs. No Man ever began the Trade of War better than young Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld;</hi> he always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd the firſt on all Occaſions, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo dangerous: and whereas Fortune was reſolv'd to be prodigal towards him, (as it will appear in the Sequel) ſhe prov'd ſo favourable to him, that his Reputation was perfectly ſettled in a ſhort ſpace of Time: He went through all Military Degrees; and tho he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd no manner of Aſſiſtance from Home, he always appear'd with ſo much Splendor, and made ſo great an Expence, that he equall'd the Chief Officers of the Army. He falling ſick of the Plague, his Gentleman of the Horſe, thinking he would never reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſold his Equipage: You may eaſily imagine his Surprize, when being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99996:7"/>cur'd, at a time every one expected his Death, his ſaid Gentleman of the Horſe acquainted him with what he had done; he would certainly have puniſh'd him ſeverely for it, had he been ſtrong enough to attempt it. But hearing that he had not as yet diſpos'd of the beſt part of his Money, he wiſely diſſembled his Diſpleaſure: Inſomuch that the ſaid Gentleman, who was one of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who ſubſiſt every where, and who knew his Maſter's Humour, made up another Equipage again, in a ſhort time, very little inferior to the Firſt; which the Count was ſo well pleas'd with, that he pardon'd him, and made uſe of him as before.</p>
            <p>The War which had now laſted five Years, ending in a Peace, Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> who hated a ſedate Life, return'd into <hi>France,</hi> and from thence went into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> where getting acquainted with Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor <hi>Cremoniny</hi> a Noble <hi>Venetian,</hi> in the City of <hi>Padua,</hi> he contracted ſo ſtrict a Friendſhip with him, that in a Year's time he profited ſo well by his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, that he has often own'd ſince, he was indebted to him for the beſt part of what he knew. After having ſeen all <hi>Italy,</hi> he went back into <hi>Germany,</hi> where
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99996:8"/>he made a pretty long ſtay; and finally, the deſire of returning into his Native Country, growing the moſt predominant of all his Paſſions, he put himſelf in the Retinue of an Ambaſſador who was going for the Court of <hi>Denmark,</hi> only to honour his Embaſſy: And by the Charms of his Perſon, as well as of his Wit, he made ſo great a Progreſs in the ſaid Ambaſſador's Favour, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd nothing from him; inſomuch that when they came to <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> he was preſent at all the Conferences he had with the Chancellor his Father: That Great Man, who thought he had loſt one of his Sons, in the Perſon of <hi>Cornifix,</hi> from whom he had never heard any News in ten Years time, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with his Wit, and admiring the Solidity of his Judgment in Affairs of State, in an Age in which moſt Men only mind their Pleaſures; whether it were by Simpathy of Blood, or out of deſire to engage <hi>Cornifix</hi> in King <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>'s Court, he conceiv'd ſo great an Eſteem for him, that after a long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference he had with the Ambaſſador, in which the Count was not preſent, he could not forbear acquainting him with the Sentiments he had for the Count,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99996:8"/>and to intreat him to let him know, how he came to engage himſelf in his Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. The Ambaſſador who lov'd him tenderly, told the Chancellor that he was a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Gentleman, whoſe Name was not very different from his, adding a great deal to the Praiſes he had already given him. But whereas the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, who knew all the Nobility of the Kingdom, could find no Family that had any Relation to the Name which the Ambaſſador told him the Count went by; he deſir'd him to grant him the Favour to diſcourſe him the next Day in private himſelf.</p>
            <p>It would be difficult to expreſs the young Count's Joy, when he heard the good Opinion his Father had of him, and to think what an agreeable Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize it would prove to him, to hear that he was that Son, whoſe ill Nature had oblig'd him to forſake. It is much eaſier to imagine than to deſcribe it; and we may eaſily conceive that it is impoſſible for two Perſons to have a greater. <hi>Cornifix</hi> waiting on the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor the next Day, according to his Deſire, he receiv'd him with all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility he could expect from a Man of his Character; and after having diſcours'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99996:9"/>of ſeveral Things in general, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor asking him what Family he was of, with an obliging Concern, which confirm'd what the Ambaſſador had told him, he excus'd himſelf for a long while, telling him that perhaps he would not be pleas'd at it, and that he was afraid he would loſe the good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he had of him, when he knew him. But whereas this Myſtery did only ſerve to increaſe the Chancellor's ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to know it; the Count told him at laſt, that he was that <hi>Cornifix,</hi> the Tenth of his Sons, whom he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake at his Governour's Solicitation. Thunder does not ſurprize thoſe who ſee it fall near them, more than this Confeſſion did the Chancellor. He held his Eyes fix'd on the Count a long while before he could utter one Word: He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd all his Features one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, endeavouring to find out ſome of his own; and could hardly perſwade himſelf, that a forſaken Child could have made himſelf ſo perfect. Joy and Shame ſtruggled ſo much in his Heart, that he was quite at a loſs: but in concluſion, Nature made him ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that he was really his Son; a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Tears guſh'd out from his Eyes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99996:9"/>and Embraces ſucceeded Civilities. As this Adventure was very Extraordinary, and as the Chancellor thought himſelf very happy, to have recover'd a Son whoſe Merit was already known at Court, he immediately acquainted King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and the Prince his Son therewith; who thereupon doubled the Favours they had already expreſs'd towards <hi>Cornifix.</hi> The Ambaſſador was not diſpleas'd at this Diſcovery, tho it hinder'd him from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the agreeable Converſation of the Count as before. And I may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that all thoſe who were Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, expreſs'd the Share they took in his Joy.</p>
            <p>Merit undoubtedly can produce much of it ſelf, and we have many Examples of Men who have rais'd their Fortune to the higheſt Degree by it alone. Young Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> had reaſon to expect all things from his, without being thought preſumptuous: But yet we muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, that the Favour of his Father, who govern'd the State, did contribute conſiderably towards his becoming a Favourite to the King and to the Prince, who could do nothing without commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating it firſt to him. Nevertheleſs tho it is natural for young Men to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99996:10"/>dazled with Greatneſs, he liv'd with more Modeſty than before; and being ſenſible that the Favour of Kings is as dangerous as pleaſing, he reſolv'd to leave the Court to go into <hi>Spain.</hi> His Equipage was ready, and his Father approving his Reaſons, he only tarried for the King's Leave to go on Board; but that great Prince who lov'd him ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, laid ſuch abſolute Commands on him not to go, that at laſt he reſolv'd to ſtay, and to uſe his utmoſt Endeavours to preſerve his Favour. Soon after this the King honour'd him with the Place of Lord-Chamberlain, which engag'd him ſtill the more particularly near his Perſon; and he diſcharg'd the ſaid Truſt ſo worthily, and ſhew'd ſo much Courage in the Naval Wars which the King had againſt the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in which two of his Brothers were kill'd, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> could not forbear expreſſing his Satisfaction to all thoſe of his Court, for having ſo accompliſh'd a Subject.</p>
            <p>As there were no Degrees at that time among the <hi>Danes,</hi> to diſtinguiſh the Nobles from one another, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Denmark</hi> being then Elective, the King's Children were the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were above the Nobility.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99996:10"/>Among the Rivals of Glory young <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifix</hi> had to deal with, <hi>Hannibal Séeſted</hi> was one of thoſe who gave him moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation: He was a very fine Gentleman, and had a great deal of Wit; ſo that being both partly of the ſame Age, and equally Ambitious, they were common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite in all Things. The King after the Queen's Death, being fallen in Love with a very beautiful Lady, of the Antient Family of <hi>Monch,</hi> call'd <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> who had all the Qualifications of a Great Princeſs, had ſhe been born one, not being able to obtain any Favours from her, had married her with all the Formalities requir'd in a Lawful Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, in the preſence of the whole Court, and of the Senate, with this Clauſe in the Contract, That the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren he ſhould get by that Marriage, ſhould not be Princes, and ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the Title of Earls of <hi>Sleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> and <hi>Holſtein,</hi> of which they ſhould have the Name and Arms, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from other Gentlemen: The Reaſon of which was, that the King having Children by his firſt Marriage, and there bring no Principality in the Kingdom; had thoſe he might get by the Second been acknowledg'd Princes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99996:11"/>they would have prov'd too great a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the Common-Wealth, becauſe they could not have marry'd with the Nobles of the Country. The Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> deriv'd her Birth from this Marriage. Young <hi>Cornifix,</hi> who till then had been a Stranger to the Power of Love, meeting in that Beautiful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all he could wiſh to raiſe his Fortune to the higheſt Degree, and to become the happieſt of Men, fell paſſionately in Love with her, at a Time when <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> was mov'd with the ſame Paſſion. Love among Perſons of Quality, is like a Beacon, which is no ſooner kindled, but it is perceiv'd at a great Diſtance; therefore the Count coming oftner to the Queen's Apartment than he us'd to do, it was thought he had an Inclination for the young Counteſs; and whereas the King's Favour, and his own Merit, gave him a great Advantage over his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, he ſoon effac'd thoſe Impreſſions which <hi>Hannibal</hi> had made in the young Counteſſes Mind: But whereas ſhe had a Prudence far above thoſe of her Age, ſhe did them Juſtice, without ſeeming to incline more towards the one than the other; and had it not been for the natural Jealouſy they had of each other,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99996:11"/>they would have had no reaſon to be jealous of the Favours they receiv'd: They were a long while before they could diſcover in favour of which the Counteſs would declare her ſelf, tho they omitted nothing to ſhew their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for her. This made the Count ſo melancholy and ſo ſad, that chancing one Day to be alone with the Counteſs, he look'd on her a conſiderable while, without being able to utter one Word: Which ſhe deſiring to know the Reaſon of, after he had excus'd himſelf awhile, he declar'd his Paſſion to her. The Counteſs being ſurpriz'd, bluſh'd at this Declaration, and looking on the Count, with a Severity capable to make the boldeſt of Men tremble, he repented his having ſaid too much; but however there was no Remedy, and the Occaſion had ſeem'd too favourable to him not to ſay a thing which he could no longer conceal: Therefore he threw himſelf at the Counteſs's Feet, humbly craving her Pardon for his Preſumption, in words ſo moving and ſo tender, that the moſt cruel of Women would have pitied him. But this word <hi>Love</hi> did ſound ſo harſh in the Counteſs's Ears, and ſhe had conceiv'd ſo frightful an Idea of it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99996:12"/>that ſhe could not bear it. The Count, on the contrary, ſaid a thouſand ſoft Things to her, to perſwade her that that Paſſion could never be baniſh'd from the World, without making it as wild and ſavage as Deſarts, ſince it was the only thing which ſupported Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and maintain'd Union even among the moſt Barbarous: And he had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly remov'd that great Averſion, had not the Queen come in, which oblig'd him to quit that Subject. The Count went away between Fear and Hope; and whereas it behov'd him to juſtify Love, before the Counteſs, the firſt time he ſaw her again, having an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſpeak to her; after a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty long Converſation, the Counteſs told him, that if he did not exceed the Bounds he had preſcrib'd to himſelf, he might hope to be hearken'd to in time: ſo that he went away extreamly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd. Some time after this, having been ingag'd in a Combat, in which he gave Proofs of his great Valour, he had the pleaſure to hear the Counteſs praiſe him in his Rival's Preſence, with ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, that he no longer doubted but ſhe had ſome Kindneſs for him. And indeed he richly deſerv'd the Praiſes the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99996:12"/>gave him, having done an Action which would paſs for a Fable, had not his King been a Witneſs of it, as well as moſt of the greateſt Men of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. It is moſt certain, that the City of <hi>Hamburgh</hi> being built upon the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Territories, they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to pay him Homage for the ſame; and that according as they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd their Power, they have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to free themſelves; ſo that moſt of the Kings have been oblig'd to take Arms, either to aſſert their Right, or to repel thoſe Rebellions: Which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd King <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> one of the braveſt Princes that ever reign'd in the North, to build the City of <hi>Glucſtad,</hi> upon the River <hi>Elbe,</hi> with a Fort capable to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Efforts of that little Common-Wealth, and to keep them in Awe; that the ſaid Prince having been forc'd to take Arms, upon the Account of ſome Things he demanded of the <hi>Hambur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;</hi> he being at <hi>Glucſtad</hi> with his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they ſet out a Fleet of ſeveral Ships, deſigning to make a Deſcent, to make themſelves Maſters of that Place; which they would have done, being ſuperiour in Number, had not the extream Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour that generous Prince, Count
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99996:13"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> and a French Gentleman who belong'd to him, ſhow'd on that Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, prevented them, they never aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning a Battery of ſome Pieces of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnance, which commanded the Port, notwithſtanding all the Gunners were kill'd or wounded, and that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that kept it retir'd into the Town, upon the continual Fire from on Board the Ships: But thoſe three Heroes choſe rather to die, than to ſuffer the taking of the Town, or to fly. And whereas nothing is impoſſible to thoſe who are capable of great Reſolutions, they made ſo great a Reſiſtance for an Hour together, that the Gariſon of the Town taking Heart again by their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Fleet being half diſabled, was oblig'd to retire, with as much Shame as Admiration; and none of them were wounded, tho the Bullets which were ſhot at them, had cover'd their Faces ſo thick with Dirt, that they were hardly to be known again. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Action juſtly deſerv'd the Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> and ſhe could not refuſe this Juſtice to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Count, ſeeing that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon this Expedition, the King had given him the Government of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99996:13"/>Iſle of <hi>Funen,</hi> to honour his Vertue; and that his very Enemies were forc'd to own, that he deſerv'd the Favour and Kindneſs of his Maſter. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from that time forward, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs had a particular Reſpect for him, and receiv'd his Addreſſes in ſuch a manner, as ſatisfy'd him that ſhe was not inſenſible: But that which made an end of winning her Heart, and of ruining <hi>Hannibal,</hi> was another Action perform'd by the Count; which being very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common, eſpecially among Courtiers, will diſcover the Character of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Soul, as well as the Violence of his Paſſion for the Counteſs.</p>
            <p>Jealouſy, which would not be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if it did not often miſtake Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances for Realities and Truths, having taken poſſeſſion of the Queen's Heart, upon a bare ſuſpicion that the King her Husband was paſſionately in love with one of her Maids of Honour, forc'd that Princeſs, whoſe Beauty was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſened by Years, to do ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary things, in order to preſerve a Conqueſt which ſhe had lawfully won, and which ſhe eſteem'd above her Life, that the King was reduc'd to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Extremity of ſuing a Divorce. In
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99996:14"/>order thereunto he aſſembled the Senate, to propoſe Means about it, leſt he might be tax'd with Injuſtice. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs <hi>Eleonora</hi>'s Tears, whom he lov'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all his other Children, could not prevail with him to alter his Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all thoſe who were at Court, forſook that unfortunate Queen, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge the King's Anger. Finally, Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> prov'd the only Man, who, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to every one's Expectation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook her Defence; he choſe rather to venture the loſs of his Favour, than to poſſeſs it, at a time when his dear Counteſs was in Affliction: and whereas he had no proſpect of Happineſs without her, after having endeavour'd in vain to appeaſe the King, Love prevail'd over Fortune; and he had the Aſſurance to tell the King, that he was in hopes to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify the Queen publickly. <hi>Hannibal,</hi> who fancy'd that the Count would infallibly ruin himſelf in taking that Party, and who was no leſs jealous of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Favour than of his Miſtreſs, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd that Occaſion to take his Poſt, and to deſtroy him in the King's Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: He omitted no Means to ſucceed therein, and to the End that all the World might know it, he alſo took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99996:14"/>him to acquaint the Senate with the King's Reaſons. The Day appointed to plead this famous Cauſe being come, the King repair'd to the Senate-Houſe, with all the Senators: The Queen and all her Children likewiſe repair'd thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with no body but Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> who was to defend them: And every body being ſeated according to their Rank, <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſtood up, and urg'd the King's Reaſons with ſo much Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and <hi>Brillant,</hi> that moſt of thoſe who heard him, ſuppos'd the Queen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ruin'd: But they ſoon alter'd their Minds, for Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> whoſe Noble Air mov'd all thoſe who ſaw him, ſhew'd with ſo much Grace and Solidity the Queen's Innocence, who had only ſinn'd through an Exceſs of Love, which can never be blam'd, ſince Exceſs alone juſtifies that Paſſion; that finally the King could not forbear mixing his Tears with the Queen's, as well as all the Senators; and coming down from his Throne, he embrac'd her, and reſtor'd her the ſame Place ſhe poſſeſs'd in his Heart before that Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. It is impoſſible to expreſs the Applauſes Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> receiv'd for this noble Action, nor the Shame <hi>Hannibal</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99996:15"/>was cover'd with, when coming out of the Senate, the Earl drew his Sword, to ſhew that Rival he knew how to uſe it as well as his Tongue: he had not the Courage to encounter him, but fled in great Diſorder and Confuſion. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs as they were the two moſt conſiderable Men of the Kingdom, the King made them Friends again; but notwithſtanding the ſaid Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hannibal</hi> ever ſince preſerv'd a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Revenge againſt the Earl, and never could forgive him that Affront.</p>
            <p>The whole Court went to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Queen, upon her being more in the King's Favour than ever; the Earl did not fail to expreſs his Joy to her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. You may eaſily imagine that ſhe omitted nothing to ſhew her Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to him for the great Service he had done her; and that ſhe us'd him with all the Kindneſs he had reaſon to expect. But that did not move him, compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to what the Counteſs ſaid to him after the Queen was gone, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had left them out of reſpect. That charming Creature, after having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated all, and even the leaſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of what had paſs'd in the Senate, aſſur'd him, that ſhe would never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99996:15"/>it; and that in caſe the King did approve his Sentiments, he would ſoon be ſenſible that ſhe preferr'd him to all the World. As I relate nothing but what is actually true, I will not puzzle my ſelf to find out fine Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to deſcribe the Earl's Anſwer, I will only tell you, that it was as witty as paſſionate; that at his coming away from the Counteſs he was the happieſt of Men; and that ſoon after it he was ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, that the King himſelf propos'd his Marriage with the Counteſs, and that he married her, notwithſtanding all the Brigues of <hi>Hannibal:</hi> neither will I give you an Account of the Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficencies which were made to honour the Wedding of thoſe Illuſtrious Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſince you may eaſily imagine that they were not Mean; beſides that, having many things to ſay, I might prove tireſome ſhould I particularize every Circumſtance.</p>
            <p>The King who (as I have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd) lov'd Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> paſſionately, being deſirous to raiſe his Fortune to the utmoſt Degree, made him Conſtable of the Kingdom, and ſoon after it Great Maſter; whoſe Power being equal to that which the Antient <hi>Maires du Palais</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99996:16"/>had, under the firſt Race of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> made the Earl the Second Perſon of the Kingdom, ſince he did exert the King's Power in his Abſence: Therefore as he had nothing more to wiſh for, he found himſelf the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Men, during the Life of King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> his Father-in-Law. He was ſent Ambaſſador Extraordinary into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> where he made himſelf more conſiderable by his Merit than by his Quality: and at his return to <hi>Chriſtian</hi>'s Court, he officiated his Place with ſo much Sweetneſs and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, that every body bleſs'd his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But thoſe were much in the right, who have ſaid, that in order to maintain a great Fortune, a ſecond is requir'd.</p>
            <p>For K. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was no ſooner dead, but the Earl's Enemies, or rather the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of his Glory, us'd their utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to deſtroy him. But whereas they were ſenſible that his Fortune was upheld, by the Honour he had of being ally'd to the Royal Family, tho the <hi>Danes</hi> had, for the ſpace of Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years and upwards, all along rais'd their laſt King's Eldeſt Son to the Throne, they endeavoured to aboliſh
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99996:16"/>that laudable Cuſtom, and in order thereunto form'd ſo powerful a Cabal, that they had the boldneſs to maintain in a Council, compos'd of the Deputies aſſembled to make the Election, that Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> could not be elected, without cauſing the abſolute Ruin of the Kingdom: But Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> who was Preſident of the Council, being ſenſible of their Deſign, aſſerted the Intereſt of the Prince his Brother-in-Law, with ſo much Courage and Eloquence, that the Elector who had propos'd the Excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſiſted as well as all the reſt; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Earl did not break up the Aſſembly until the Prince was elected King. It is true, that in order to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe thoſe who ſeem'd to be moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfy'd, he ingag'd, by virtue of his Office of Great Maſter, he being the Head and Protector of the Nobility, that the Prince would preſerve all their Privileges, and that their Grievances ſhould be redreſs'd. The Election was made on this Condition, as it had been done time out of mind. In the mean time, Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> being ſatisfi'd with his having perform'd his Duty, without valuing himſelf upon it, by publiſhing the ſame, not having acquainted the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99996:17"/>Prince before nor after the Election, with all the Brigues that had been made to exclude him from the Crown, his Enemies made uſe of his Modeſty to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him; for having perſwaded the King that he himſelf had aſpir'd to the Crown, becauſe ſome Votes had been given for him, and that not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obtain his Ends, he had, in order to make himſelf the more recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, caus'd the Election to be made on the Conditions I have mention'd.</p>
            <p>This wrought ſo powerfully on the King's Mind, that he was thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from his Favour in a Moment, without knowing the Reaſon of it; and the ſaid Coldneſs made ſo much noiſe, that the Earl's Enemies finding the King diſpos'd to believe all their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, had the Malice to ſeduce a Woman, call'd <hi>Dina,</hi> who had an acceſs in the Royal Family, to accuſe the Count and the Counteſs his Wife, of having made Solicitations to her to poiſon the King, the Queen, and all the Royal Family.</p>
            <p>This Monarch giving too much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the ſaid Accuſation, without ſtaying for any farther Informations, wrote to the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99996:17"/>Princes of the Empire, and to the P. of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> to give them an Account of the ſaid Conſpiracy, and to deſire their Advice how to proceed againſt thoſe Traitors (for ſo he call'd the Count and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs) who were in his Power; deſiring them to rejoice at Heaven's having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd him from that Treaſon. But whereas the Quality of the Perſons ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd, oblig'd him to obſerve ſome For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities; he allow'd them to make their Defence before the Council, leſt the World ſhould think he deſign'd to oppreſs them.</p>
            <p>It was on this Occaſion this Great Man diſcover'd an undaunted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Firmneſs of Mind; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcovering the leaſt Trouble in his Countenance, he made his Defence with ſo much Judgment, that the ſaid Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and Captain <hi>Walter</hi> who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd her, not being able to reſiſt the Force of the Earl's Reaſons, were fully convicted of Perjury: <hi>Dina</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to loſe her Head, and <hi>Walter</hi> to a perpetual Exile; which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly put in execution.</p>
            <p>The Earl finding by this Proceeding that his Ruin was reſolv'd upon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible by the King's Eaſineſs to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99996:18"/>believe ſo ſtrange an Accuſation againſt a Perſon of his Quality, that he would be eaſily diſpos'd to give Credit to all the Calumnies of his Enemies, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to provide for his own Saſety, and that of all his Family.</p>
            <p>In order thereunto, he reſolv'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into <hi>Poland,</hi> hoping to be ſafe there; and having propos'd his Deſign to the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> that generous Lady would needs follow him, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Reaſons he could urge to the contrary, which could never prevail over her Affection for him.</p>
            <p>All things being diſpos'd for their departure, the Counteſs put on Mens Clothes as well as one of her Women, the only One ſhe took along with her; and going on board one of their own Ships, after having been ſome Days at Sea, they were ſurpriz'd by ſo dreadful a Storm, that they thought themſelves loſt: But after having ſuffer'd all the Hardſhips imaginable for two or three Days time, they came to an Anchor in the Road of <hi>Dantzick,</hi> where they landed. The Earl being thus ſafely got on Shore, diſpatch'd one of his Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> to intreat the King to allow him a Retreat in his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99996:18"/>Kingdom, and to protect him againſt his Enemies. He remain'd at <hi>Dantzick</hi> in expectation of his Return, where the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> ſtill keeping on her Mens Clothes, in order to divert her Sorrows, made ſome Addreſſes to a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Quality, who did not want Charms, and whoſe Converſation was very agreeable; and her Courtſhip made ſo ſtrong an Impreſſion on the Lady's Heart, that ſhe could no longer live without her.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the thing proceeded ſo far, that the Lady's Husband being grown jealous, the Counteſs would certainly have brought her ſelf into Trouble, but that the Gentleman whom Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi> had ſent to the Court, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd with a Refuſal, they reſolv'd to repair to the Queen of <hi>Sweden.</hi> The Counteſs having acquainted the ſaid Lady therewith, ſhe was ſo ſtrangely mov'd at her departure, that after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid the moſt tender Things to her, to oblige her to tarry, ſhe was reſolv'd to follow her, had not the Counteſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd her Sex to her. You may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gueſs her Surprize at this unexpected Confeſſion, and what different Paſſions her Soul was agitated with: Shame,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99996:19"/>Spite and Rage, tormented her by turns, and the Counteſs ſtood in need of all her Wit to appeaſe this abus'd Woman; but in the end, her Love being turn'd to Friendſhip, they parted with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proteſtations, of loving each other to the Grave.</p>
            <p>The Earl, whoſe Courage was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted, was overjoy'd to ſee the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs divert her ſelf thus: So that thoſe Illuſtrious Perſons, did bear their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with as much Conſtancy, as they had ſhown Modeſty in their Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>The Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> who knew their Merit, and did pity their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, having aſſur'd the Earl's En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy that ſhe would grant them her Protection, they repair'd to <hi>Stockholm,</hi> where that great Princeſs kept her Court at that time.</p>
            <p>She receiv'd them with all the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they could expect from her Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity; particularly the Counteſs <hi>Eleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora,</hi> who not having quitted her Man's Clothes, a Dreſs in which the Queen often delighted her ſelf: She was ſo much taken with her Air, that ſhe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nothing to expreſs her Joy to her, for being able to aſſiſt her. After
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99996:19"/>the Earl had paid his firſt Reſpects to the Queen, he told her that he only begg'd her Protection on this Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he would ſubmit to her Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and that he would anſwer, before her Majeſty, to whatever Accuſations ſhould be made againſt him.</p>
            <p>She granted his Deſires, ſo that they remain'd two Years at <hi>Stockholm</hi> in quiet: but when they thought their Enemies had no longer any thoughts to perſecute them, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Ambaſſador receiv'd an Order to accuſe the Earl of ſeveral Crimes, the leaſt of which would have coſt him his Head had he committed it: but tho the Ambaſſador deliver'd a Letter to the Queen, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſign'd by the King's own Hand, in which he conjur'd her to puniſh Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld;</hi> She allow'd him to make his Defence before the Council: and having ſent him a Copy of the Heads of the Accuſation, on the Day appointed by her Majeſty to plead the Cauſe, the Earl diſcover'd his Innocence by ſuch convincing Proofs, that the Queen, and all the Senators, were ſatisfy'd of it; and the Ambaſſador was ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, that not being able to make a poſitive Reply to the Earl's Defence, it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99996:20"/>turn'd his Brains; and he left the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil in that Diſtraction, without taking his Leave of the Queen, and without ſhowing the leaſt Civility to the Lords of the Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>So publick a Juſtification, put the Earl's Enemies into ſo great a Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that their Perſecution lay dormant for ſeveral Years, during which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd with his Family into <hi>Pomerania,</hi> where he had a conſiderable Eſtate, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the Sweetneſs and Tranquillity which a Country-Life can afford a Man who is tir'd with the Fatigues of the Court; and whereas he fanci'd that the Cauſe of ſo long a Silence could only proceed from the King his Brother-in-Law's being convinc'd of his Innocence, he advis'd the Counteſs to go to <hi>Copen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hagen,</hi> there to make her Court aſſidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and to endeavour to put her ſelf perfectly into the King's Favour again.</p>
            <p>But tho the Earl had written ſeveral Letters full of Submiſſion and Reſpect, that unfortunate Lady was no ſooner come to the Frontiers of the Kingdom, but ſhe was inform'd that her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had ſent Forces to the firſt Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage through which ſhe was to paſs, to ſecure her.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99996:20"/>
            <p>However, whereas ſuch an Attempt had no Precedent, and that the Counteſs could not imagine, that they could treat a Perſon of her Quality with ſo much Cruelty, ſhe continu'd her Journey, whatever her Servants could ſay to the contrary. But as ſoon as ſhe was got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little Plain, one of her Gentlemen acquainted her, that a Company of Foot was coming towards them with great ſpeed: Whereupon the Counteſs no longer doubting but that the Advice ſhe had receiv'd was true, order'd her Coach to turn about, and ſhe ſtood in need of the utmoſt Vigour of her Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to rejoin the Bridg which ſeparates the Territories of <hi>Denmark</hi> from thoſe of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> where the ſaid Souldiers, who came within Musket-ſhot of her, remain'd full of Confuſion at their not having been able to execute their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>The Earl being equally ſurpriz'd and troubled at this new Diſgrace, writ to the Court again to know the Reaſon of it; but he receiv'd no Anſwer, which made him ſenſible that it was an Effect of the Cruelty of his Enemies, who were reſolv'd, at any Rate, to keep him for ever out of the Kingdom, in order
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99996:21"/>to poſſeſs his Places, and to enjoy the great Eſtates they had made themſelves Maſters of: Which unworthy Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made him reſolve to take Arms under <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whoſe Protection he had alſo taken after the Queen's Abdication, in hopes thereby to be reſtor'd to the Poſſeſſion of part of his Eſtate. It was not without a great deal of Grief he found himſelf reduc'd to the Neceſſity of employing his Courage and his Wit againſt his Prince and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law; thoſe two Qualities did long oppoſe within his Soul the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he had taken, and they did not want Reaſons to break it; but finding no other way for his Reſtoration, he was oblig'd to embrace it.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Earl being forc'd by all manner of Reaſons to behave himſelf thus, made uſe of his Courage and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to ſatisfy <hi>Charles</hi> that he did act Sincerely. The firſt Proof he gave him of it, was the Reduction of the Iſle of <hi>Funen,</hi> which did ſubmit to him in ſo little time, that the News of it came to <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> before they knew that <hi>Charles</hi> deſign'd to conquer it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, as if Heaven had join'd with the Earl to revenge the Injuſtices
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99996:21"/>he had receiv'd, the Sea freezing to that degree, that the Artillery could ſafely be drawn over it, he perſwaded the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> to march againſt <hi>Copenhagen</hi> with Three thouſand Horſe, and Six pieces of Ordinance, not doubting but the boldneſs of the Enterpriſe would cauſe a ſtrange Conſternation.</p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>Frederick</hi> was ſo much ſurpris'd, to ſee an Army before the Gates of his Capital City, that his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage fail'd him; and in that Diſorder, the moſt effectual way he could think on, to prevent the Ruin of his State, was to oblige Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Agents to let him know, that in caſe he could mediate a Peace, he would reſtore him to the Poſſeſſion of all his Places and Eſtate. Whereas Neceſſity only had oblig'd him to take Arms againſt his Country, his Friends found him ſo well diſpos'd to forget all the Injuries he had receiv'd, that tho he was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that nothing but the preſent State of Affairs oblig'd <hi>Frederick</hi> to behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus, he made ſo good a Uſe of the Credit he had acquired with <hi>Charles,</hi> that he oblig'd him to make a Peace, which was ſign'd at <hi>Roſſchild.</hi> By the ſaid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99996:22"/>Peace, the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> yielded the Province of <hi>Schonen</hi> to the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> together with the Fortreſſes of <hi>Gabub, Hallen, Blechin,</hi> the Town of <hi>Drontem,</hi> and ſome others; and granted Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> and all thoſe who had followed him, a General Pardon, and reſtor'd him to the Poſſeſſion of all his Places, Dignities and Eſtates. After which, the two Kings embrac'd, with great Demonſtrations of Friendſhip. <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> alſo expreſs'd his good Will to the Earl, in ſuch a manner as made every body believe that he did it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely; and at Night the two Kings ſupp'd together at <hi>Frederixburg,</hi> one of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Pleaſure-Houſes, with the Queen and the Chief Officers of the two Armies.</p>
            <p>The following Day the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> after having conferr'd ſome Hours with <hi>Frederick,</hi> went for <hi>Gottemburg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the Earl remaining with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> every body did conclude, that he was as much in the King's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour as ever.</p>
            <p>But whereas <hi>Frederick</hi> was ſuſceptible to all ſorts of Impreſſions, and that the Earl's Enemies did dread the Loſs of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99996:22"/>their Credit, by the Reſtoration of his Authority, they caſt new Suſpicions into the King's Mind, which oblig'd the Earl to retire upon the Eſtate he had in the Province of <hi>Schonen.</hi> The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> being deſirous to ſhow the Earl (who was become his Subject) the Eſteem he had for him, gave him the County of <hi>Sylburg,</hi> for him and his Heirs Male for ever.</p>
            <p>But the Earl who was in hopes, by this voluntary Retreat, to make the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſenſible of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of his Perſecutors, and of the Innocence of his Conduct, was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtaken in his Conjectures; for he had hardly enjoy'd for ſome Months, the ſweetneſs which a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Life affords to thoſe who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of it, before the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> being reſolv'd to renew the War, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to him to take Arms again, with ſuch advantagious Conditions, that any Man but the Earl would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have accepted them. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he refus'd them generouſly, and made <hi>Charles</hi> ſo ſenſible, that having no new Cauſe to complain of the King, his Brother-in-Law, he could not ſerve
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99996:23"/>againſt him, without wounding his Honour, that that Great Prince, who knew the Merit of the Earl, would not oblige him to do it by Force: But whereas his admirable Qualifications had rais'd Envy againſt him among the greateſt Lords of <hi>Sweden,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thoſe who were Penſionaries to <hi>Frederick,</hi> they made uſe of that Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ruin him in the Opinion of <hi>Charles:</hi> And they put ſo malicious a Gloſs upon the Earl's good Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that having repreſented them to him, in a different manner from what he had conceiv'd when he approv'd them; and no body having made an Anſwer to juſtify the Count, they rais'd ſuch ſuſpicions againſt him, for having refus'd the great Advantages he had offer'd him, that <hi>Charles</hi> was almoſt perſwaded that he deſign'd by his Credit, to cauſe thoſe new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, not fully ſettled as yet, to revolt, in order to regain the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>'s Favour. The Earl's Enemies went further yet; for having, by ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, got an Order from <hi>Charles</hi> to the Governor of <hi>Malmo,</hi> he ſecur'd the Earl and all his Family; and upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99996:23"/>this bare Surmiſe, the County of <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> was taken from him again, which <hi>Charles</hi> had given him not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Moreover, they did confiſcate three other conſiderable Eſtates, with all his Goods, which were of an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable Value; and Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling dangerouſly ill at the ſame time, ſome diſaffected Hiſtorians did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, that he had poiſon'd himſelf for Grief, and that he was dead, or had lock'd himſelf up in ſome uninhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Place: But it was nothing but a Continuation of the Malice of his Enemies, for he had no reaſon to put himſelf to death, nor to abridg ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> having allow'd him to make his Defence publickly, he receiv'd this new Diſgrace without the leaſt aſtoniſhment; and I can affirm, that neither <hi>Eleonora</hi> nor himſelf did ever look upon it otherwiſe than as the leaſt of thoſe they had receiv'd. Soon after their being ſecur'd in their own Houſe, the Earl was cited to appear before the Senate of <hi>Malmo;</hi> but not being able to repair thither, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Indiſpoſition, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99996:24"/>
               <hi>Eleonora</hi> undertook his Defence; and whereas ſhe had an Eloquence which is not common among thoſe of her Sex, and as much Judgment as Wit, ſhe made the Senate ſo ſenſible of the Malice of their Enemies, and of the Earl's Innocence, that he was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly abſolv'd of the Crimes which were laid to his Charge; and the Senators were ſo much charm'd with what ſhe had ſaid, that they ſent her Speech to the King, together with their Judgment, to be confirm'd.</p>
            <p>A Copy of it is fallen into my Hands, which is as followeth.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99996:24"/>
               <head>The Counteſs <hi>ELEONORA</hi>'s Speech, to the Senate of <hi>Malmo.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</salute>
               </opener>
               <q>
                  <p>WERE Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to make his Defence before Judges leſs famous for their Capacity and Juſtice, or were he guilty of the Crimes he is accus'd of, his Health not permitting him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to juſtify himſelf, he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have imploy'd ſome Orator to anſwer the Eloquence wherewith his Enemies have endeavour'd to fully his Reputation: But whereas he is conſcious of no Crime, I come here, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> to diſcover his Innocence to you, and to intreat you, by a natural and plain Diſcourſe, to reſtore his Liberty.</p>
                  <p>My Husband is accus'd of Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude towards the King, becauſe he refuſes to accept the advantageous Offers that are made to him by that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99996:25"/>Great Prince, to oblige him to take Arms again for his Service; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Chief of the Nobility of <hi>Scandinavia</hi> often come to viſit him, his Enemies pretend that he deſigns to engage them to a Revolt, in favour of the King my Brother, in order to put himſelf into Favour again; and on pretence of the pretended Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, which, they ſay, they hold together, to ſucceed in the ſaid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, of which there are no Proofs, he has been ſeiz'd in his own Houſe. Truly, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> were this true, I own that Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> would be very guilty, and that he would deſerve a rigorous Puniſhment: But if I can make it appear to you, that it is a meer Calumny, has he not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to expect an entire Abſolution from your Juſtice, which may diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Innocence to all the World? Yes, I am confident of it, ſince I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it already in your Eyes; and the Noble Impatience you diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to do him Juſtice, is a certain proof thereof.</p>
                  <p>I am oblig'd in this Place, in order to juſtify my Husband, to renew all my Afflictions, and to tell you things
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99996:25"/>which, without doubt, you are but too well acquainted with, I mean the greateſt Perſecution that ever was. Be pleaſed therefore, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> to give me leave to tell you, that Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s extraordinary Qualifications, having procur'd him the Eſteem and Good-Will of the late King <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> my Father, at a time when I was marriageable, that Great Prince would needs inſpire the ſame Sentiments into me, by deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him for my Husband; and in order to enable him to ſupport the high Honour to which he rais'd him by his Alliance, he made him Great Maſter of his Kingdom, which was the moſt conſiderable Dignity next to Royalty. Tho the Earl us'd that great Fortune with all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of a wiſe Man, he could not hinder Envy from raiſing many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt him; that cruel Envy which will not ſuffer true Merit to live in Proſperity, omitted no Means to overthrow our Happineſs; his moſt innocent Actions were cenſur'd, and had not the King, my Father, been perſwaded of his Fidelity, our Perſecutors would have inſpir'd the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99996:26"/>ſame Suſpicions into him, which, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Death, they have put into the King my Brother's Mind.</p>
                  <p>That Prince was no ſooner rais'd to the Throne, but he gave too much Credit to the invenom'd Speeches of thoſe Barbarians; he loſt all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Affection he had for my Husband and for me, without our knowing the Cauſe of it; and upon the bare Depoſition of a corrupted Witneſs, he was ſo fully perſwaded that we did deſign to poiſon him, and all the Royal Family, that without conſidering that we had the Honour to be related to him, and that thoſe ſort of Crimes require very Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Proofs, he cauſed us ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be ſeiz'd, and order'd the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to proceed againſt us. But Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> having prov'd our Innocence, and that far from harbouring any ſuch abominable Thought, he was partly the Cauſe of the King's being Elected, having couragiouſly oppos'd the Brigues which were made to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him from the Crown: He was publickly abſolv'd of that Calumny, and the Woman condemn'd to loſe her Head; which was accordingly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99996:26"/>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs tho this ought to have open'd the King's Eyes, to ſee that theſe things were only done with a Deſign to embroil the Royal Family, and to create Diſorders in the State; inſtead, I ſay, that ſuch a Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to have reſtor'd us to his Favour, it only ſerv'd to exclude us from it for ever: Moreover, it prov'd a new Pretence to perſecute us; all our Cares prov'd vain, to ſhew that we did no-wiſe reſent that Injury, and that we were ſatisfy'd that our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence was known. This was look'd upon as a piece of Diſſimulation; our Submiſſions were rejected, as Snares which were laid on purpoſe to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our Revenge in time; and we were reduc'd, in order to avoid the continual Conſpiracies of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who requir'd our Blood, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire under the Protection of the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> which the Laws of the Country allow'd us to do, in hopes that the ſaid Retreat would evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Moderation of our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>But, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> this was ſo far from producing the Effects which we did expect from it, that,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99996:27"/>on the contrary, it increas'd the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe who deſir'd our Ruin; and they found ſuch Diſpoſitions in the King's Mind for their Malice to work upon, that they oblig'd him to ſend Orders to his Ambaſſador at Court, to accuſe my Husband of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Crimes, the very remembrance of which ſtrikes me with Horror: but having again clear'd himſelf of this new Calumny, his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence only ſerv'd to make him the more unhappy; for his Enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing of his Ruin by the Way of Juſtice, prevail'd with the King to diſpoſe of his Places, and to ſeize upon our Eſtate. This laſt Misfortune de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving us of Means to ſubſiſt, oblig'd C. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> after the Queen's Abdicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to engage himſelf in the Service of the King her Succeſſor, in hopes by his Arms to recover part of our Lands.</p>
                  <p>He perform'd (and it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grief I am forc'd to ſpeak it) Actions of Conduct and of Valour, which did not a little contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the obtaining of the Victory over his Country-men, and to make the King's Arms triumphant: He thereby gain'd his Eſteem and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99996:27"/>And, finally, I may ſay, that it was by his Means a Peace was made between the two Crowns, with ſo much Advantage for his Majeſty. I own at the ſame time, that my Husband was rewarded for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and that a General Pardon was granted for him and all his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; with a particular Clauſe, That all his Eſtate ſhould be reſtor'd to him; which has been perform'd ſince by the King my Brother.</p>
                  <p>The King your Maſter added to that Act of his Juſtice, a new Favour, which was the Gift of the County of <hi>Sylburg,</hi> to my Husband and his Male Iſſue for ever: And ſoon after that, the King gave us leave to retire upon the Eſtate we have in this Province of <hi>Schonen,</hi> which remain'd to him by the Peace. I own that theſe are Favours which did exceed our Hopes, and which ſhow the King's Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity; but at the ſame time I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that no body can put us in mind of them to convince us of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty is willing to renew the War, and offers my Husband con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Advantages to take up
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99996:28"/>Arms again againſt a King, to whom he has the Honour of being Brother-in-Law; he humbly craves his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would be pleas'd to excuſe him, becauſe the Articles of the General Pardon have been punctually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd. Whereupon Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld's</hi> Enemies make uſe of the ſaid Refuſal to ruin him, and make a Capital Crime of a thing, which of all things in the World is the moſt praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
                  <p>And indeed, <hi>Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> is not the Moderation which my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhows on this Occaſion, worthy of Praiſe, ſince that notwithſtanding the Reaſons he has to complain, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes the Means to reſent the Offences he has receiv'd, and does not accept Advantages which are ſo great, that they might dazle the moſt Ambitious, and make them attempt any thing to deſerve them? Neceſſity only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd my Husband to take Arms, in hopes that by the Means of a Peace, which ought always to be the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal End of a War, he might recover his Eſtate for the Subſiſtence of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. That Peace has been made by his Mediation; his Eſtate has been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99996:28"/>to him; why then ſhould he be oblig'd to take up Arms again, ſince the main Reaſon he had to do it ſubſiſts no longer? Advantages, they ſay, are offer'd to him, which he refuſes; and that is a certain Sign he deſigns to take the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>'s part again, and therefore it behoves the King to ſecure his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to uſe him as an ungrateful Man. Ah! <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> can ſuch ill Conſequences be drawn from ſo good a Reaſon? Can a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue be accounted a Crime? and muſt my Husband be puniſh'd before-hand, as if he were already convicted? No, it is impoſſible, without overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Rules of Equity and of Juſtice; and I have reaſon to believe, that you will judg more favourably, than thoſe who have ſurpris'd his Majeſty, in giving him ſuch unjuſt Suſpicions.</p>
                  <p>My Husband's Enemies prevail with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to take his Imployments and his Eſtate from him, without having convicted him of any Crime; he deſires the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the ſame for his Subſiſtance: he is refus'd, whereupon he joins
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99996:29"/>with the King, who is in War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; no body can blame him, ſince it is very natural to ſeek out Means to preſerve one's Eſtate and Life.</p>
                  <p>He mediates a Peace; in that we may ſay he is deſerving, and that his Country is oblig'd to him. Finally, by means of this Peace, he obtains what he did propoſe in taking Arms. There is not the leaſt Crime in all this: But, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> could any one excuſe him at preſent, ſhould he engage a-new under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Advantages that are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to him?</p>
                  <p>Would not that Ambition which alone could induce him to it, be blame-worthy? and would not his Country, which pities his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, have reaſon to alter their Wiſhes for his Welfare, and to loſe the good Opinion they have of his Vertue? Would not the King, my Brother, have a juſt Cauſe to ſeize our Eſtate a-new, and to turn all the Suſpicions he has receiv'd againſt my Husband into Certainty? And, finally, would not Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> make a Breach to his Honour, never to be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99996:29"/>repair'd again? I own that he has perhaps reaſon to believe that a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Pardon has only been granted to him by Force, and that the ſame Hatred is preſerv'd againſt him as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but though he were certain of it, that ill Example would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, and the ſenſibility we na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally have for thoſe of our Blood would upbraid him eternally for having violated it. Suppoſe he had it not, could he without Horror contribute towards the abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his Country, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Glory of which has been ſo dear to ſo many great Men, that Hiſtory is full of a thouſand Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Examples, which inform us that they have preferr'd it to their own Lives?</p>
                  <p>What better Party could Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> take on this Occaſion, than a Retreat and a Country Life? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to chuſe another, and if I may ſay ſo, he can form no wiſhes but for a Peace.</p>
                  <p>If his Country and his Blood, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire him with Love on one Side; the Favours he has receiv'd from the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99996:30"/>King, and the Kindneſs he has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd to him on ſo many Occaſions, oblige him to remain in the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he is in. Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> is not ignorant, that Benefits (being Acts of good Will, which create Pleaſure and Joy in the Perſon who gives, as well as in him who receives) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſo deeply engraven in the Heart of both, that they can never periſh: he is ſenſible that this agreeable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of giving, and of receiving, produces a Kindneſs which is the ſtronger, by reaſon that being Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, it ſurpaſſes that in ſome Meaſure which we are oblig'd to have for our Relations.</p>
                  <p>Finally, he is perſwaded that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude is a Crime ſo hainous, that all Nations have been ſeiz'd with Horror at the thoughts of making Laws to puniſh it. Not but that it is deteſted by all Mankind, or that by that want of Laws they deſign'd to approve it; but becauſe Benefits can never be ſufficiently eſteem'd, by reaſon that the Value of them only conſiſts in the Will of him who gives, and not in that which is the Object of it.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99996:30"/>
                  <p>That Crime has been condemn'd by a publick Hatred, and it has been plac'd among thoſe things which are to be puniſh'd by Divine Juſtice. How is it likely then, that Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi> having ſuch reaſonable Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch a perfect Knowledg of the King's Favours, ſhould form Cabals to make Provinces revolt, which eſteem themſelves too happy to be under his Dominion? Can he hinder the Nobility, whoſe Head he was formerly, from coming to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him in his Diſgrace, and to pity his Misfortunes? Muſt their Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be imputed to him as Crimes, and without the leaſt Proof being given of the Correſpondence that is ſuppos'd between the King my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and him, without any Body's juſtifying that he has excited any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, or proving that he has given his Majeſty any prejudicial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, Muſt he be ſo unhappy as to loſe his Majeſty's Favour? No, <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Lords,</hi> I cannot believe it, ſince Words, though never ſo fine or agreeable in the Mouth of an Orator, are not ſufficient to convict my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, nor to perſwade that he is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99996:31"/>Guilty. On the contrary, I have reaſon to hope that you will approve his Deſign of remaining in his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, and of wiſhing a good Peace between the two Crowns, ſince it is the only thing he can do with Juſtice, in the deplorable Condition to which he is reduc'd: Therefore I expect his Juſtification from you, <hi>moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</hi> to the End that the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confirm'd by his Majeſty, we may be reſtor'd to our Liberty, and to the Injoyment of our Eſtate, as well as put in poſſeſſion again of the County of <hi>Sylburg:</hi> that all the World may be ſenſible that that great Prince ſtill eſteems Count <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> and that he does not think him unworthy of the Continuation of his Favours.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The K. of <hi>Sweden</hi> was at <hi>Gottenburgh</hi> when he receiv'd the News of C. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Abſolution; and after having read the Letter which the Senate did write to him, and the Counteſs's Speech, whoſe Wit he admir'd as well as her Affection for her Husband; he immediately or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd one of his Secretaries of State to write the Confirmation of it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd ſo much Joy to all his Court for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99996:31"/>his being found Innocent, that thoſe who had devis'd that Calumny remain'd in the higheſt Conſternation.</p>
               <p>But the Artifice which <hi>Hannibal Seeſted</hi> made uſe of to be reveng'd of the Earl, and to render the King's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ineffectual to him, muſt needs move the Indignation of all the World againſt him: This Barbarian, who was become his Brother-in-Law, having marry'd one of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi>'s Siſters; and who notwithſtanding their Reconciliation, and the Ties of Blood, preſerv'd in his Heart a mortal Hatred againſt Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> ſince the Time he drew upon him, as I have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: This <hi>Hannibal,</hi> I ſay, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of a ſuppos'd Diſcontent, was at the K. of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Court at that Time to give <hi>Frederick</hi> an account of his Deſigns, feigning an extream Joy at the Succeſs of the Earl's Affair, though he was one of the chief Authors of it; intreated <hi>Charles,</hi> with all the earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imaginable, to put the Letters of Confirmation into his Hands, that he might be the firſt to acquaint Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> with this agreeable News. The King thinking he was in earneſt, grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him the Favour he deſired; but he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99996:32"/>inſtead of performing what he had promis'd, writ to the Earl, that though he had prov'd his Innocence, the King was ſtill ſo incens'd againſt him, that without any one's being able to diſcover the Cauſe of it, he had reſolv'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him from the place where he was kept, to put him into ſome Priſon diſtant from all ſort of Correſpondence: and colouring this Perfidiouſneſs with a ſtudy'd Tenderneſs, he conjur'd him to endeavour his Eſcape by all the Means he could poſſibly think on, to avoid the Storm which threatned him ſo near, and to ſecure his Family, ſince it was impoſſible he ſhould not make his Peace, ſince the Senate had abſolv'd him.</p>
               <p>The Earl receiving this Letter before his Friends had given him an account of the Truth (becauſe <hi>Hannibal</hi> had ſent it by an Expreſs) not having the leaſt Suſpicion that a Brother-in-Law could be unfaithful to that degree, eaſily gave Credit to it.</p>
               <p>Upon the receipt of this News, the Counteſs and he looking on the Danger to be preſſing, without expecting any farther confirmation of it, only thought how to deceive their Keepers, to make their Eſcape.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99996:32"/>
               <p>As the thing was pretty difficult, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Account of the great Number of Soldiers which guarded them, this Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Unfortunate Couple, having communicated their Deſign to the Earl's Gentleman of the Horſe, nam'd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa,</hi> they did conſult a long while for ſome Expedient, without being able to find a good One.</p>
               <p>But at laſt <hi>Daranda</hi> calling to mind that he had formerly obſerv'd, that the Houſe had a ſecret Out-let in a by-Street, they reſolv'd that he ſhould try whether they could make uſe of it, while they did imploy themſelves on their ſide to ſecure their Papers and their Money. All things being diſpos'd thus, the firſt thing <hi>Daranda</hi> did was to hire a Sloop, to go out of the Port at any Hour: and having diſcover'd by his Search in the Houſe, that going down into the Cellar, there was a Door of Communication with another Cellar, and from that Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar into another Place, out of which they might ſet out without being ſeen by the Guards, he immediately acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Earl therewith.</p>
               <p>But whereas there was a Centry at his Door, and that the Counteſs was in a different Apartment from his, the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99996:33"/>Difficulty was to deceive that Centry, which chang'd hourly, which made the thing almoſt impoſſible, they not daring to confide in him.</p>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Volume.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99996:33"/>
            <head>The LIFE of CORNIFIX, COUNT of ULFELD, Great Maſter of DENMARK: And of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> his Wife.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
            <p>THE Count and his Gentleman of the Horſe, dexterouſly looſn'd ſome of the Boards which made the Partition of his Chamber, and having made a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Overture, dreading Viſits might
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99996:34"/>break his Meaſures, he ſent to his Guards to deſire them not to admit any Body into his Chamber becauſe he was very much indiſpos'd: Inſomuch that being ſafely got out about Six in the Morning, they went into the Cellar, where the Earl having put on the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of a Prieſt, which <hi>Daranda</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for him, they croſs'd the Town and reach'd the Key without any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and the Earl being got on board the Sloop which the ſaid <hi>Daranda</hi> had hir'd, which kept at a diſtance from the reſt, he went back to the Counteſs, in order alſo to facilitate her Eſcape.</p>
            <p>But whereas it was Day before he came back, he met with great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being oblig'd to lead her through the great Gate, her Apartment being too diſtant from the Cellars: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs as Neceſſity is the Mother of Invention, the Counteſs who has a great deal of Wit, immediately found out an Expedient which did ſurpriſe <hi>Daranda,</hi> as much as he found it fit for his deſign. The Habits worn by the Towns-Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being abſolutely different from thoſe of Women of Quality, inſomuch that they would deceive the moſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, the Counteſs reſolv'd to put
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99996:34"/>on one of thoſe Habits, in order to get out.</p>
            <p>Having in order thereunto ſent for one of the ſaid Women who liv'd hard by her, under pretence of diverting her ſelf with her, and whoſe Shape was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like her own; the Counteſs chang'd Clothes with her, notwithſtanding all the reſiſtance ſhe could make, and her Servants found her ſo well diſguis'd, that they judg'd their Enterprize infallible: And indeed tho they had upwards of thirty Soldiers to deceive, the Counteſs having a Set of very unruly Horſes, which <hi>Daranda</hi> had ſet looſe on purpoſe, they made ſuch a terrible noiſe in the Yard, that all the Soldiers ran out to help the Grooms to retake them, ſo that there only remain'd a Centry to deceive, who ſtood at the Counteſs's Chamber-Door: but one of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs's Chamber-Maids ſeigning to have loſt a Diamond of great value, which ſhe was looking after with great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſaid Soldier was ſo much mov'd at it, that he would needs help her to ſeek for it; which opportunity the Counteſs and <hi>Daranda</hi> took to get out without the leaſt hindrance: And their Eſcape was manag'd with ſo much Art,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99996:35"/>that the Soldiers never perceiv'd it till the next day, when they were got to <hi>Copenhaguen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was very reaſonable to believe, both upon the account of the General Pardon, as well as becauſe the Earl had refus'd to ingage himſelf anew with the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that his retreat to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen</hi> would be attended with no ill Conſequences, and that <hi>Frederic</hi> would keep his Word and let them live in Peace.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs it prov'd quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for within three days after their Arrival, without knowing what new Crime they had committed, they were ſeiz'd in their own Houſe, and carry'd into the Iſle of <hi>Bornholm,</hi> ſituated in the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, between the Province of <hi>Schonen</hi> and <hi>Livonia.</hi> It was in that Iſland the Count and Counteſs were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd into the hands of the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous of Men, call'd <hi>Fowlk,</hi> who was Governor thereof. They were no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his power, but this Barbarian, without the leaſt regard to their Birth, took all their Jewels and Money from them, and then lock'd them up in a Dungeon in which they were hardly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to breathe. This ſtrange way of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99996:35"/>proceeding made them ſenſible that the Sequel could never prove favourable, and indeed they were not deceiv'd in their opinion of this Governor's Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For after having depriv'd them of the Nouriſhment which he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to give them, he took all their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen from them, and only left them that which they had on, which being rotten in a ſhort ſpace of time by reaſon of the dampneſs of the Dungeon, they were reduc'd to a new torture, and finally not to have Bread enough to ſuſtain a Life, which they would have put a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to, had not the Laws of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty forbad them ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But his Barbarity proceeded further yet; he refus'd to allow the Earl a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and the Counteſs a Maid to wait upon them, and he abus'd his Power with ſo much Inſolence, as to add ill Words and Reproaches to his ill Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Moreover, the Patience which thoſe Illuſtrious Captives expreſs'd du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the eleven Months they remain'd together, inrag'd this Cruel Governor to that degree, that after having exert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Tyranny over their Bodies, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to torture their Minds: He part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them becauſe they did ſuffer with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99996:36"/>too much Conſtancy, and remov'd them into two Dungeons which were one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver another; but becauſe they had Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows on the ſame ſide, and that loving each other tenderly, they could ſpeak to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in order to deprive them of that only remaining ſatisfaction, he caus'd their little Windows to be damm'd up, depriving them at once of Light, and of the pleaſure of converſing together. The Counteſs being no longer able to bear this Treatment, fell ſick, and her Illneſs increas'd to that degree that ſhe concluded her Death to be at hand, and even then he had much ado to allow her a Woman to take care of her.</p>
            <p>But tho the Counteſs earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated this Tyrant to ſend her a Prieſt to adminiſter the Sacrament to her, neither her Tears nor Intreaties could prevail with him; and tho ſhe offer'd to make her Confeſſion aloud before him, he refus'd her that only Comfort. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens deſigning her for greater Sufferings yet, reſtor'd her Health at a time when ſhe did leaſt expect it. About that time the Woman whom the Governor had ſent to take care of her in her Illneſs, told the Counteſs, that ſhe was ſo much concern'd to ſee the Earl and her ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99996:36"/>to ſuch a miſerable ſtate, that ſhe was reſolv'd to facilitate their Eſcape.</p>
            <p>But whereas the thing was almoſt impoſſible, by reaſon of their ſeparation, and of the danger of coming down to the Sea, which beats againſt the foot of the Tower in which they were lock'd up; the Counteſs rejected the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſhe made to her about it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were that ſhe fear'd ſhe had a mind to ſurprize her, or that ſhe really thought the thing impoſſible.</p>
            <p>But the Woman perſiſting to aſſure her that ſhe was ſincere, the Counteſs found an Expedient to acquaint the Earl therewith; and he to let her know that he would neglect nothing on his ſide to improve this favourable Occaſion, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Counteſs having made Sails with her Sheets, while the Earl made Oars with ſome of the Wooden-Bars of his Dungeon, with ſo much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, that he could conceal them in his Clothes, and yet make as good a uſe of them as if they had been larger; and having alſo made a kind of Ladder with the remainder of his Sheets and ſome old Ropes, they imploy'd it ſo well that with the aſſiſtance of the ſaid Woman who lay in the Counteſs's Dungeon,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99996:37"/>they got down to the foot of the Tower, and going along the Strand they found a little Boat, in which they enter'd; and having fix'd their Sails and Oars, they did commit themſelves with Joy to an Element, which ſeem'd to them leſs barbarous than the Governor.</p>
            <p>But whether the aforeſaid Woman thought them ſafe, or that the fear of being puniſh'd by the Governor made an impreſſion upon her mind, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with the Evaſion of the Count and Counteſs.</p>
            <p>The day was half ſpent, and they were already got upwards of four Miles from the place whence they put out to Sea, without having met with the leaſt Accident, when the Governor, who could not imagine how they had made their Eſcape, getting on board a Sloop, with ſome Soldiers, made ſo much haſte that the Earl and the Counteſs were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by that Barbarian, who had ſo much Brutality in his firſt Tranſport, as to give the Earl, nay even the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, ſeveral Baſtinado's; and after having fetter'd them like Slaves, he carry'd them back to their Dungeons, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately diſpatch'd an Expreſs to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> to acquaint him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99996:37"/>
            <p>Soon after this the King ſent Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> to viſit them, who was their Capital Enemy, and did at that time injoy Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Place; but when he came into his Dungeon, he did not know him, by reaſon of the Alteration which the ill treatment he had receiv'd during fifteen Months had occaſion'd in him, and the ill Clothes which he was cover'd with. Inſomuch that inquiring of him where Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> was, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Earl anſwering that he was the Perſon, tho he was his Enemy, he could not forbear weeping, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſenſibly concern'd: But when this firſt motion, which Horror and Pity had excited in his Soul, was over, Hatred reſuming the place it had held there ſo long, he told Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> with an imperious Tone, That he came from the King to tell him that he ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition his Majeſty to obtain his Liberty; and that of the Counteſs his Wife. The Earl having deſir'd Pen, Ink and Paper in order thereunto, which was granted him; after he had written the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he deliver'd it to Count <hi>Rantzaw;</hi> but he pretending that it was not ſubmiſſive enough, becauſe he would force Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> to write another, the draught of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99996:38"/>which he had brought from <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> he told him diſdainfully, giving him the ſaid Draught, That the only way to obtain his Liberty, was to write thus.</p>
            <p>The Earl obſerving that they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him, in the ſaid Draught, to beg pardon for ſeveral Crimes which he had never thought on, far from having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them, told Count <hi>Rantzaw,</hi> That he could never reſolve to ſign it, eſpecially becauſe the Counteſs his Wife was included in it, who was only a Priſoner becauſe ſhe lov'd him with too much Tenderneſs: but tho this would have prevail'd with a Generous Mind to deſiſt from ſuch an Unjuſt Proſecution; he perſever'd during ſix Weeks time he tarry'd in <hi>Bornholm</hi> in the reſolution of obliging the Count to ſign it by Force or good Will.</p>
            <p>But at laſt being tir'd with Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s reſiſtance, he told him haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That unleſs he ſign'd it, he ſhould loſe his Head, as well as the Counteſs, without any Trial. Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> who had never known what it was to fear Death, would freely have ſubmitted to it, rather than to ſign, had not the Love he had for the Counteſs withheld him:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99996:38"/>But this great Man finding that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance put her Life in danger, ſuffer'd far greater Torments in the Conflict he had within himſelf, than thoſe which are indur'd by Death; for his great Courage having forſaken him, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd long ſpeechleſs, and it was with a great deal of trouble and grief he ask'd Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> at laſt, what Crimes he had committed to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd thus, and why they were not brought to their Trial according to the Laws of the Kingdom?</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Rantzaw,</hi> who was no great Politician, being ſurpris'd at this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, made no other Anſwer to Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> but that he ought to remember that he had been ingag'd under the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the General Pardon, he ſhould be puniſh'd: To which he anſwer'd, That it was a Violation of the Law of Nations; at which Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> flew into ſuch a Paſſion, that after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid many things to him which he durſt not have thought at another time, he left Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> in his Dungeon, and went back to Court.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99996:39"/>
            <p>The only advantage they receiv'd by Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi>'s Viſit was, that at his return their Governor was chang'd, in whoſe room the King ſent Colonel <hi>Skro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> whoſe Moderation and good Nature allay'd their Affliction ſo much, that notwithſtanding they did ſtill remain in the ſame Dungeons, they did not ſuffer near ſo much by it, becauſe he took care to viſit them, and to allow them whatever they ſtood in need of Some Months being ſpent thus, <hi>Skroder</hi> receiv'd Orders from Court, to put his Priſoners at Liberty, provided they would ſign a Paper which was ſent to him: he thinking that this would be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very welcome piece of News to the Earl, immediately repair'd to him, and told him with great Civility, That i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would be his own fault if he was not ſoon at Liberty, ſince a Ship was ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from <hi>Copenhaguen</hi> for them. The Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſiring time to read the Paper which he had brought him, and to anſwer it, the Governor withdrew and told him, That he did allow him the remainder of the Day to think ſeriouſly upon it. But whereas the Title of the ſaid Paper was a <hi>Reverſion,</hi> the Count was ſeiz'd with dread and horror at it, and indeed it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99996:39"/>was not without reaſon, ſince it was indeed the moſt Cruel Reverſion that Fortune could ever cauſe; it did not only oblige him to renounce the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of ſeveral Eſtates, to the value of upwards of Three Millions; to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don his Places, his Goods, his Debts, and his beſt Jewels; but that which was more cruel than all this, it did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Counteſs to renounce the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and Arms of Counteſs of <hi>Sleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> and of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> which the late King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> her Father had given her; and finally it made the General Pardon contain'd in the Treaties of Peace void, in relation to Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> and his Succeſſors. The next Day, whilſt the Earl was reading this ſtrange Reverſion, the Governor came in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſeen by him, who obſerving that he ſtill remain'd in the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, ſaid to him, Well, Sir, what are you reſolv'd to do? To die, ſaid the Earl, turning briskly about, rather than ſign a thing which is far more cruel than Death; neither indeed can I live much longer, conſidering the ill Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I have receiv'd from your Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor; and I ſhould purchaſe a Liberty
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99996:40"/>which I cannot enjoy with Honor, at too dear a rate.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora</hi> is as much concern'd in this buſineſs as my ſelf, be pleas'd to carry this Paper to her, and to tell her, That I find the Conditions of it ſo harſh and ſo crue that I will never ſign it unleſs it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably ſoftned.</p>
            <p>This honeſt Gentleman, who was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much concern'd at the unjuſt Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of thoſe Illuſtrious Perſons, went ſtrait to the Counteſs, to whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Earl's Reſolution. After ſhe had examin'd the ſaid Writing very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly for ſome hours, ſhe told the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, returning it to him, That ſhe was very much troubled at it; but that ſhe would approve whatever the Ear did in ſuch a diſmal Conjuncture. The following Day <hi>Skroder</hi> went to the Ear again, and having entreated him, with Tears in his Eyes, ſpeedily to take his Reſolution, becauſe he could tarry n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> longer: The Earl anſwer'd, That he found that Writing ſo ſhameful for al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Family, that he had rather expect the utmoſt Effects of his Enemy's Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty in his Dungeon, than reſolve to ſign ſo Infamous a thing: And adding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99996:40"/>to all this, what he had already ſaid to Count <hi>Rantzaw,</hi> That he wonder'd they did not bring him to his Trial, in order to ſeize all his Eſtate by a lawful Confiſcation; the Governor told him, That he had Orders to ſend back the Ship and the Writing, in caſe he made the leaſt difficulty to ſign it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he had no more time to loſe. But whereas the Count alledg'd ſtill new Reaſons for which he could not do it; the Governor told him, That unleſs both he and the Counteſs did ſign it, he was afraid the Court would final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolve to put them to Death.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe reminding the Earl of what Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> chanc'd one Day to ſay to him in the heat of their Conteſtations, That the Court had been ready more than once to ſend a Warrant for their Execution in Priſon; it made him reflect more ſeriouſly upon it, and he deſired the Governor to allow him a little time more to confer with the Counteſs about it, which was granted him.</p>
            <p>It was then about Noon, and the Weather was ſo calm, that the Earl com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe to the Grate of his Window, he call'd the Counteſs, who heard him
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99996:41"/>inſtantly, becauſe they never fail'd to ſpeak to one another when the Winds, which are high in that Country, allow'd them ſo to do.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs deſiring to know his Pleaſure, and the Earl ſaying, Muſt we die, or ſign what you have read? The Counteſs who underſtands, and ſpeaks ſeveral Languages, reply'd immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe <hi>Latin</hi> Verſes,
<q>
                  <l>Rebus in adverſis ſacile eſt contemnere mortem,</l>
                  <l>Fortius ille facit, qui miſer eſſe poteſt.</l>
               </q> It is eaſy to deſpiſe Death in Adverſity, but he ſhews moſt Courage who can ſuffer Miſery.</p>
            <p>The Earl who admir'd the force and preſence of her Mind, and who was ſenſible that had not the Maxims of Chriſtianity withheld her, ſhe would undoubtedly have done, what the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Aria</hi> did under the like Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, asking her again, Whether this was all ſhe had to ſay? the Counteſs added this other Verſe,
<q>Accidit in puncto, quod non ſperatur in anno.</q>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99996:41"/>That may happen in a moment which we could not expect in a Year: And told the Count that this was her Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Earl not being able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend whence ſhe could have this glimmering, or this point of hope, as ſhe call'd it, in ſo evident a deſpair of their Fortune, they being lock'd up in Dungeons, their Family diſpers'd and wandering, from whom all manner of Subſiſtence was taken away; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd long ſpeechleſs, without reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on what he was to do. But at laſt he fancy'd there was ſomething ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natinal in this, and according to that beam of Hopes, which the Counteſs darted out like a Flambeau to light him, he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it and ſign'd this Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he gave to the Governor, for the Counteſs to do the ſame, which ſhe did accordingly.</p>
            <p>It is difficult to expreſs the Joy thoſe Illuſtrious Captives felt, to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of their Dungeons, and the Tenderneſs they expreſs'd to each other on this occaſion: I ſhall only ſay, that after having been long without being able to utter one word by reaſon of the Agitation which Grief and Love had excited in their Hearts; the Tears
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99996:42"/>which they ſhed for their Misfortune, ſucceeded their Silence: And finally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having embrac'd each other tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they did exhort one another to bear their Diſgrace in ſuch moving words, that the by-ſtanders ſeem'd no leſs affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted than themſelves.</p>
            <p>Night being come, they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd in the Ship I have mention'd, where they were ſtrictly guarded by twenty Muſqueteers, until their Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> where they were conducted to Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi>'s Houſe, in an Apartment prepar'd on purpoſe for them. The following Day about Ten at Night, the Count did viſit them, and told them from the King, That his Majeſty having thought fit to change ſomething in the Reverſion they had ſign'd; he did command them to make another, to ſeal it with their Seals; and to date it from <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> which they did, tho they were ſenſible that it was only done to perſwade the Publick, that they had done it without being forc'd to it.</p>
            <p>But after this, Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> having again propos'd an Oath of Fidelity to be ſign'd by them, which was conceiv'd in ſtrange terms; Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> could
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99996:42"/>not forbear telling him, It was a very uſeleſs thing, ſince that conſidering the Condition to which his Ill Fortune had reduc'd him, he might more reaſonably be reckon'd among the Dead than the Living.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> who was pleas'd to inſult over him, putting himſelf in a Paſſion, told him diſdainfully, That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they did ſign it, they ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd back to <hi>Bornholm,</hi> where they ſhould periſh in their old Dungeons; inſomuch that the Earl not daring to make the leaſt Reply to that cruel Threatning, ſign'd whatever he pleas'd.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the Earl and the Counteſs had bought their Liberty at the rate I have mention'd, they could not injoy it, and they were confin'd in the Iſle of <hi>Funen</hi> until new Orders.</p>
            <p>The only Favour that was granted them, was to carry their Family along with them, and to diſpoſe of the Income of the Eſtate of <hi>Ellensburg,</hi> which was worth about Twelve Thouſand Livers <hi>per Annum,</hi> which the King allow'd them for their Subſiſtence.</p>
            <p>This Violation of Faith will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſeem ſtrange to every body, and indeed it ſhocks Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99996:43"/>Laws: Nevertheleſs conſidering the then ſtate of Affairs, the King was oblig'd in Policy to behave himſelf thus, and I ſhould freely excuſe all the other Perſecutions Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> has met with, if they had had as reaſonable a foundation according to the Maxims of State. The King had a mind to make his Kingdom Hereditary: Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> by his Merit, and by his Reſentment, was the only Man capable to oppoſe it, had he been at liberty; becauſe he had abundance of Relations and Friends who durſt not expreſs their good Will towards him, but who would certainly have ſided with him at that time, as well as moſt of the Nobles. Therefore it was the King's Intereſt not to releaſe Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> in order to proſecute his deſign, which I will now give you a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of. All the World knows that the laſt Wars between <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> had exhauſted the laſt in all Reſpects to that degree, that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was reduc'd to the utmoſt extremity of Miſery; eſpecially the third Eſtate, the Nobles being excus'd from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Impoſitions, which excited a mortal hatred in the Commons againſt them: The Nobles were alſo very much
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99996:43"/>humbled for want of a Head to lead them, and to aſſert their Privileges, by which the Kings were kept in awe, and the Peaſants like Slaves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Nanſen,</hi> firſt Burguemaſter of <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> a Man of ſence, very rich and daring, and who did abſolutely govern the Citizens, conceiv'd the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Deſign to free the People from Slavery, by making the Kingdom He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary. But whereas the ſaid Deſign requir'd a great deal of Prudence and of Speed, and that he could not manage it alone, he diſcover'd it to <hi>John Swan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> his Friend, who by his Merit and his Eloquence had acquir'd as much Credit over the Clergy, as he had over the Third E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Men acting with great Secrecy on their reſpective ſides, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all things ſo well, that they ſecur'd the Votes of the Chief of the Clergy and of the Citizens, to whom they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd Rewards ſutable to the Services they ſhould receive from them: But whereas they had not a ſufficient acceſs to the King, they diſcover'd their Secret to <hi>Chriſtopher Gabel,</hi> a Man whom For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had rais'd above the Common, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99996:44"/>made him Favourite to <hi>Frederick,</hi> who undertook nothing without his Advice. <hi>Gabel</hi> was over joy'd to find ſo favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Occaſion to ſignalize his Zeal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King, and to be reveng'd of the Imperious Humour of the Nobles, who often upbraided him with his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction.</p>
            <p>Therefore having confirm'd <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swaning</hi> in their Reſolution, they held ſeveral ſecret Conferences toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about this Affair; and whereas the Neceſſities of the State oblig'd the King ſhortly to convene the Aſſembly of the Eſtates of the Kingdom; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Cuſtom of the Kingdom, the ſaid Aſſembly was to be held in the Iſle of <hi>Funen; Gabel</hi> told the King, that for ſeveral important Reaſons, which his Majeſty would approve of, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to hold it at <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> which was reſolv'd upon notwithſtanding the Reſiſtance of the Nobles.</p>
            <p>The Overture thereof being made, <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swaning</hi> repair'd to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where <hi>Gabel</hi> tarry'd for them: As ſoon as they came into the King's Chamber, <hi>Gabel</hi> told his Majeſty, that they had a Buſineſs of great conſequence
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99996:44"/>to impart to him, and that in order thereunto it was neceſſary to give him a ſecret Audience: whereupon every body was order'd to retire, and <hi>Nanſen, Swaning</hi> and <hi>Gabel,</hi> being by themſelves with the King, <hi>Nanſen</hi> told his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in few words, That the great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nobles was the only cauſe of all the Diſorders of the State, becauſe the Counſels which depend on many commonly prove uſeleſs, either by reaſon of their delays, or becauſe they are ſeldom kept ſecret.</p>
            <p>Moreover that the Citizens and the Country People being no longer able to maintain all the Expences of the State alone, without having the leaſt ſhare in the Adminiſtration of Affairs, they were reſolved for the Common Good to make the Kingdom Hereditary, to the end that all the Authority being inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one Perſon, which is the moſt perfect Form of Government, every Man might hope to be advanc'd by his Majeſty according to his Merit.</p>
            <p>The King being extreamly ſurpris'd at this Propoſition, told <hi>Nanſen</hi> that he look'd upon it as a thing impoſſible, and that in caſe they did undertake it, it would coſt them their Heads, without
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99996:45"/>his being able to hinder it: That he did not think fit to venture any thing, by reaſon of the fatal Conſequences that Affair might be attended with. <hi>Nanſen</hi> reply'd boldly, That things were brought to that paſs, that they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go through; or reſolve to die; that they were certain of the good Will of the Clergy, and of the People, and that they only beg'd his Majeſty's Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and would take all the reſt upon themſelves. The King between Fear and Hope, having told them that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd all to their Conduct, retir'd into his Cloſet, in expectation of that Revolution, which did aſtoniſh all <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſecure two Crowns to his Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swaning,</hi> being perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they ſhould be well rewarded, retir'd very well ſatisfy'd, to give Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the execution of their Deſign. As they were croſſing the Bridg of the Caſtle to go to the Chancery, they met <hi>Otho Krag,</hi> Knight of the Order of the Elephant, and Miniſter of State, who obſerving ſomething extraordinary in their Looks, ſtopt them haughtily, ſaying, Whence come you? I ſee that you are caballing; but take heed, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99996:45"/>ſo ſhew'd them the blue Tower with his hand, as if he deſign'd to give them to underſtand that they ſhould be lock'd up there: To which <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> barely anſwer'd, we ſhall ſee, and continu'd their way.</p>
            <p>That very Afternoon the Eſtates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled, the King deſir'd them to conſider of ſome Means to ſuſtain the extraordinary Expences of the State. The Nobles excus'd themſelves from contributing towards it, alledging their Privileges, which freed them from all ſorts of Impoſitions: The Clergy alſo alledging theirs, and the Commons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that they would no longer pay any Duties unleſs the others alſo contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted towards them, they broke up, ſo much exaſperated againſt each other, that <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swaning,</hi> who had promoted theſe Diſputes, ſeeing their Friends very well diſpos'd, <hi>Nanſen</hi> put the Citizens under Arms, and <hi>Swaning</hi> having aſſembled the Deputies of the Clergy, they prevail'd with theſe two Eſtates to offer the King the Hereditary Soveraignty of the Kingdom; and without loſing time they beſieg'd the Nobles in their Houſes, threatning to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99996:46"/>deſtroy them unleſs they gave their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto.</p>
            <p>The Nobles being ſurpriz'd at this bold Propoſition, which deſtroy'd their Authority, endeavour'd to make ſome reſiſtance; but the Citizens perſiſting in their Reſolution in a manner which made them ſenſible that they would get nothing by force, they deſir'd time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the next Day, which was granted them.</p>
            <p>The People kept to their Arms all the Night, and <hi>Nanſen</hi> ſhut the Gates of the City, and placed Guards in the chief parts thereof, ſo that by break of Day the Nobles were ſummon'd to give in their Declaration.</p>
            <p>Accordingly Fourteen of the Chief among them gave it in the form deſir'd by the two Eſtates, and having ſealed it with their Seals, <hi>Nanſen</hi> and <hi>Swaning</hi> with the other Deputies carry'd it to the King, who did not expect ſo favourable an Event.</p>
            <p>But the ſaid Declaration not being thought full enough, the Nobles were ſummon'd in the King's Name to make it more poſitive: The City-Gates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd cloſe all the while, and finally the Nobles finding that there was no
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99996:46"/>Medium, and that unleſs they did grant the King's deſire, they would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the fury of the People, whoſe hatred they were not ignorant of, in that extremity they did conſent to grant the King, and his Succeſſors the Hereditary Soveraignty of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and the Three Eſtates having ſign'd the Act, they went together to preſent it to <hi>Frederic,</hi> and did ſubmit all their Privileges to him, to diſpoſe of them at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The King receiv'd them very graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and having promis'd to uſe them kindly, he made them hope for a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier Reign than they had injoy'd till then: After which the Royal Family repair'd to the Cathedral Church there to ſing <hi>Te Deum,</hi> where <hi>Swaning</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented them at the Door, with an Eloquence which procur'd him the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of all his Auditors.</p>
            <p>The Publick Ceremony was deferr'd for two days longer; a Theatre was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, on which the King, the Queen, the Princes and Princeſſes their Children being conducted, the King being ſeated on a Throne under a rich Canopy, the Chancellor made a Speech to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about the Behaviour they were to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99996:47"/>obſerve under this new form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and about the Oath they were to take to the King and his Children.</p>
            <p>After which the Nobles, the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks, and the People, having taken the Oath of Allegiance, the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty expreſs'd a world of Joy, inſomuch that the <hi>Danes</hi> ſeem'd to have loſt the remembrance of their paſt Miſeries; which ſhows what power Novelty has over Mens Minds, who always hope by Revolutions, either to eaſe their Afflictions, or to ſatisfy their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The King would alſo needs make a Publick Feaſt for every body; but, whereas the Nobles were at the charge of it, it was obſerv'd that moſt of them did not come to it, and that among thoſe that did, ſome refus'd to eat, ſo that the Clergy and the Citizens only expreſs'd their Joy and Satisfaction at it: It laſted ſome Days, after which the City-Gates were open'd to every body.</p>
            <p>Thus the whole State was alter'd in leſs than a Fortnight by the Conduct and Reſolution of <hi>Nanſen, Swaning</hi> and <hi>Gabel.</hi> The King in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them for that great Service,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99996:47"/>erected the Church of <hi>Copenhaguen</hi> into an Archbiſhoprick in favour of <hi>Swan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and augmented the Revenue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of proportionably.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty made <hi>Nanſen</hi> firſt Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Senate and Bourgrafe, which ſignifies Earl or Chief of the Burghers, and gave him as well as to <hi>Gabel</hi> ſeveral conſiderable things. And whereas the Burger-maſters had alſo contributed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably towards this great Revolution, the King gave them the Injoyment of the Territory of <hi>Rotskild,</hi> which is worth upwards of a hundred thouſand Livers <hi>per Annum,</hi> and granted the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Copenhaguen</hi> ſeveral great Privileges, and among the reſt the power of poſſeſſing Fiefs; which till then had only been allow'd to the Nobility.</p>
            <p>During theſe Tranſactions, Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> and all his Family were at <hi>Ellens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> in <hi>Funen,</hi> where he endeavour'd to recover his Health, which was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impair'd by the Ill Treatment he had receiv'd at <hi>Bornholm;</hi> no longer concerning himſelf with the Affairs of the World. Neither was he mov'd in the leaſt when he heard this Overthrow of all the Antient Privileges of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, for the preſervation of which, at
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99996:48"/>
               <hi>Frederick</hi>'s Election he had incurr'd his hatred, and had ſince been expos'd to all his Misfortunes: And in order not to leave the King the leaſt ſuſpition of his preſerving any Reſentment, he beg'd his leave to go to <hi>Spaw,</hi> there to take the Waters, which was granted him.</p>
            <p>Accordingly Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> and the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> with all his Family left <hi>Ellensburg,</hi> to go into the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> where after having ſeen ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Towns, the Earl finding that the Air at <hi>Bruges</hi> did agree better with him than any other, he reſolv'd to ſtop there. The Earl had not been there above ſix Months, when he was inform'd that Colonel <hi>Fowlk</hi> (that Cruel Governor who had us'd him ſo barbarouſly in his Priſon at <hi>Bornholm</hi>) was come there to viſit his Relations; but whereas his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition did not permit him to call him to an account, the Earl acquainted his Eldeſt Son therewith, who was at the Academy at <hi>Paris,</hi> who taking Poſt immediately, being fir'd with a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous deſire to revenge his Father's Wrongs, made ſo much haſte, that he reach'd <hi>Bruges</hi> on the very day <hi>Fowlk</hi> was to go away from thence; ſo that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99996:48"/>meeting him in his Coach, he attack'd him alone amidſt all his Servants, and kill'd him, without being wounded.</p>
            <p>This ought to teach thoſe who have Imployments, not to abuſe their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and above all to keep within the bounds of reſpect towards Perſons of Quality in Affliction; this bold Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on met almoſt with a general Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation at <hi>Copenhaguen:</hi> The moſt Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and thoſe who were not influenc'd by Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Enemies, prais'd the Son's Courage for having undertaken it. But whereas the King was ſtill afraid of the Earl, his Enemies improv'd that occaſion to raiſe a new Crime againſt him, and perſwaded his Majeſty mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, that he would never have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd to revenge himſelf thus, had he not been ſure of the Protection of ſome Potent Prince. The King's Natural Timorouſneſs, being join'd to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents of ſeveral Noblemen who had a mind to take Arms, made <hi>Frederick</hi> reſolve to ruine Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and the better to colour the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, they accus'd him of having made Offers to the Elector of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> to dethrone the King, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him with his Crowns; which was
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99996:49"/>a thing he had not ſo much as thought on, and yet this was the laſt pretence of his Perſecutions, as it will appear by the Sequel.</p>
            <p>Some Months after <hi>Fowlk</hi>'s Death, Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> deſir'd the Counteſs <hi>Eleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora</hi> to go into <hi>England,</hi> there to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a conſiderable Sum which was due to him. This Generous Lady, who had no ſtronger application in the World, than to ſhare all her Husband's Misfortunes, ſeeing him overwhelm'd with Sickneſs, made no difficulty of undertaking that Journey, and without conſidering whether the conſequences of it would prove favourable to her or not, ſhe ſet out towards <hi>London.</hi> The King who was gloriouſly reſtor'd at that time in his Kingdoms, and who had gone through many Misfortunes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, being thereby the more inclin'd to pity others, receiv'd the Counteſs with all the Civility and Reſpect imaginable; and his Majeſty being inform'd of the Subject of her Journey, order'd his Miniſters to give the Counteſs ſpeedy ſatisfaction, in ſuch an obliging man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that ſhe had reaſon to believe, ſhe ſhould not tarry long for her Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99996:49"/>
            <p>But finding, after a Month's ſtay, that the Miniſters ſtill put her off from day to day, and not being able to appear at Court with all the Grandeur due to her Birth, ſhe thought ſhe could tarry there no longer without ſhame, inſomuch that ſhe reſolv'd to return to the Earl her Husband, and ſo took her leave of the King, who us'd her as civilly at her Departure, as he had done at her Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, expreſſing a great deal of concern at her not being paid.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs went back for <hi>Dover</hi> again, where ſhe arriv'd the ſecond day, in hopes of going back for <hi>Flanders,</hi> but ſhe was ſtrangely ſurpris'd when being got on Board to continue her Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſhe was ſeiz'd by a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who carry'd her to <hi>Copenhaguen.</hi> As the Counteſs did not expect this U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that new Misfortune affected her more ſenſibly than all the reſt had done; for tho ſhe had ever appear'd Invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhe then abandon'd her ſelf ſo much to her Grief, that all thoſe who ſaw her were mov'd with Compaſſion. But whereas her Tears were uſeleſs, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd Pen, Ink and Paper, and making a Generous Effort over her Grief, ſhe writ the following Letter to the Earl.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99996:50"/>
               <head>The Counteſs <hi>ELEONORA,</hi> to Count <hi>ULFELD.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <q>THE Misfortune which is befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len me, not having been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen by either of us: I do not doubt, Sir, but it will afflict you more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly than all thoſe we have already undergone, ſince you are not to ſhare it with me, and that our Separation was the only thing that could exhauſt our Conſtancy. Yes, my dear Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, I ever thought my ſelf above Grief and Fortune, while I ſuffer'd with you, becauſe your Courage ſupported my Weakneſs, and that I found wherewith to comfort my ſelf in your Converſation. But ſince I am now forc'd away for <hi>Denmark,</hi> contrary to the Law of Nations, and all that is moſt ſacred in the World, I find that I am no longer Invincible, and that our Enemies have found my Foible. It is neither the fear of a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99996:50"/>Dungeon, nor the ſight of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that makes me tremble; I am too much us'd to the unjuſt Effects of their Rigour to dread them. But when I think that I ſhall never ſee you more, that Cruel Thought cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates ſuch Violent Tranſports in me, that I ſhould willingly reſign my Languiſhing Life to have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of taking my laſt leave of you. Alas! Sir, how weak is Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when Love oppoſes it? And how uſeleſs is Wiſdom, when Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs poſſeſſes a Heart? 'Tis vain to ſay, That we ought to arm our ſelves againſt the worſt Events; That we muſt bear them patiently, and put our ſelves above the reach of Fortune: thoſe Precepts make no impreſſion upon a tender Soul, when it loſes what it loves, and when it has much knowledg, it only ſerves to authorize our Tears inſtead of ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them. However tho I now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to you, that that Conſtancy which you have ſo often commended in me, has left me on a ſudden; and that in loſing you, I condemn my ſelf to weep the remainder of my Days, for the only Loſs that could afflict
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99996:51"/>me: It is not reaſonable that you ſhould imitate me, and that you ſhould ſhed continual Tears, to the remembrance of my Misfortune. Great Men are not forbidden to ſhed Tears, but they muſt be ſparing of them, or rather they muſt ſtifle them to preſerve the Opinion the World has of their Courage. Every body knows that you have born your Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes without ſhowing the leaſt alteration of Mind, and that you look'd upon them rather as a Subject to exert your Vertue, than as a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to grieve. Why then, Sir, ſhould you forfeit ſuch a Noble Reputation, becauſe I am fallen into my former Chains again? No, no, Sir, I love you too well to ſuffer you to make ſuch a breach to your Glory; and provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you lock up all your Grief for my Misfortune within your Heart, 'tis all I deſire. Therefore do not ſigh at the News of my Captivity, all our Children are with you; and if it be true that nothing on Earth is more capable to perſwade than Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, teach them betimes to bear their Ill Fortune patiently, ſince it is the only Good you can do them in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:99996:51"/>your preſent Circumſtances: Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them all for my ſake, leſt a long Abſence ſhould blot me out of their Memory; uſe them to name me of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that they may remember I am their Mother: But above all things be perſwaded that I will never do any thing unworthy of my Birth, nor of our Friendſhip; and that tho our Enemies have found the way to part us for ever, they cannot hinder me from Dying your Faithful Partner.</q>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>ELEONORA.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Counteſs had hardly made an end of her Letter, when the Captain came to tell her that it was time to go; ſo that loſing all hopes of Deliverance, ſhe call'd for <hi>Daranda</hi> that faithful Squire, and after having ſhed many Tears, ſhe took a Bracelet of Diamonds from her Arm, and gave it him with the Letter: Here ſaid ſhe, deliver this to my Husband, and deſire him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me, and to take care not to fall into the hands of our Enemies like me; and above all things to bear this
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99996:52"/>new Misfortune with the ſame Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage he has born all the reſt. Ending theſe Words ſhe went into the other Ship, and <hi>Daranda</hi> who dreaded the like Misfortune for his Maſter, went back to him with as much ſpeed as if he had had good News to carry to him.</p>
               <p>At his Arrival at <hi>Bruges,</hi> he found this Illuſtrious Infortunate in his Cloſet reading ſome Letters he had receiv'd from <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> where in notice was given him that being anew accus'd of ſeveral Crimes, eſpecially for the Death of Colonel <hi>Fowlk,</hi> and of keeping Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> he had been condemn'd that very day to ſuffer exquiſite Torments, and that Mon were in ſearch of him to execute the ſame on his Perſon, as they had done on his Effigies.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Count ſaw <hi>Daranda,</hi> he imagin'd by the trouble which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in his Countenance, that he brought him ſome Tidings yet more vexatious than thoſe he had already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd: Therefore as king him where the Counteſs was, inſtead of anſwering he only ſhew'd him the Letter and the Bracelet, not being able to utter one word: After the Earl had read the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99996:52"/>Letter, he only ſaid, Good God, when will you ceaſe to afflict me? Then ſunk down in a Chair, where he remain'd upwards of half an hour without any motion.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs as ſoon as he recover'd out of this Swoon, he read the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs's Letter over again with great At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and having order'd <hi>Daranda</hi> to prepare his Equippage to go away the next day, he apply'd himſelf with great Tranquillity on his ſide to order his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
               <p>The following day all things being ready, he went away towards <hi>Baſle</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where he remain'd four or five Months almoſt always ſick, without diſcovering himſelf.</p>
               <p>As for the Counteſs ſhe was conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Copenhaguen</hi> with Civility enough, which put her in hopes that they had better Sentiments towards her at Court than before; but ſhe was no ſooner landed, but Colonel <hi>Allefeld</hi> came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her, and carry'd her to the Tower of the Caſtle, where ſhe was lock'd up with a poor Woman to wait upon her.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99996:53"/>
               <p>That which is moſt ſurpriſing is, that ſome Perſons having told her, in order to diſcover her thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Husband, that he was alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd, ſhe look'd into her left Hand, and anſwer'd, that it was not true, but that he would not live long.</p>
               <p>And indeed as the King was ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> ſhould diſturb him about the new Revolution of his State, which had diſoblig'd all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, <hi>Frederick</hi> omitted no means to ſecure him: And ſeveral Perſons were in ſearch of him, whereever they thought they could hear from him.</p>
               <p>So that upon a falſe Report which was ſpread at <hi>Baſle,</hi> that there were Perſons in ſearch of the Count, tho he was very ill, he put himſelf at Night in a ſmall Veſſel on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> in order to repair to <hi>Briſac</hi> where he thought he ſhould be ſafe.</p>
               <p>But that Infortunate Earl had hardly travel'd ten Leagues, before the great Cold penetrated his dying Body, which was depriv'd of Natural Heat: and thus he ended that Languiſhing Life, which his Enemies had ſo often endeavour'd to ſnatch from him by their Injuſtices, without being aſſiſted by his Children,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99996:53"/>and by his antient Servants, whom he had ſent away in the Morning by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Roads.</p>
               <p>Thus dy'd <hi>Cornifix</hi> Count of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> about threeſcore Years of Age, leaving three Sons Succeſſors of his great Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, of whom the Eldeſt who turn'd <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> has apply'd himſelf to the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Service. The ſecond is Knight of <hi>Maltha,</hi> and the third lives in <hi>England,</hi> who is one of the moſt Accompliſh'd and moſt Learned Gentlemen in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All thoſe who have known Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi> grant, that he was one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Men of his Time, and that had it not been for his Ambition to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf King, after the Death of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> his Father-in-law, he would have been the happieſt Lord of the North: But tho ſome Hiſtorians that are ill inform'd, or have been brib'd by his Enemies, have accus'd him of Treaſon, and of being guilty of all the ill Succeſſes which his Brother-in-Law <hi>Frederick</hi> has met with in his laſt Wars, I hope the World will judge more equitably, ſince he has done nothing but what the Laws of the Country allow'd him to do. And finally let no body accuſe me of having
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99996:54"/>made a Panegyrick inſtead of writing an Hiſtory. I grant, that the late King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> having publickly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd the ſmall Value he had for Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> his Son, and that the Nobles not being able to accuſtom themſelves to the Imperious Humour of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs his Wife of the Houſe of <hi>Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> perhaps by reaſon of their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy with the <hi>Germans,</hi> Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> being perſwaded by the Counteſs <hi>Eleono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> (who had had ſome particular falling out with the Princeſs her Siſter-in-Law) had ſome thoughts of making himſelf King, inſtead of Prince <hi>Frederick,</hi> and took ſome meaſures in order thereunto: But beſides that that was very excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a Man like him, ſome Nobles having propos'd the Excluſion of Prince <hi>Erederick,</hi> Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> who was an admirable Politician, finding his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures broken, and being ſenſible that he was not powerful enough to maintain a Civil War alone, wiſely turn'd the Scales, and caus'd Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> to be elected on conditions which made him ſhare his Authority, under pretence of preſerving the Privileges of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, of which he was the Head, by virtue of his Place of Great Maſter. But
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99996:54"/>if <hi>Frederick</hi> had reaſon to complain of Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> on this Account, he alſo fail'd on his ſide, by giving too much Credit to the Calumny of <hi>Dina</hi> and of <hi>Walter,</hi> which he ſhould have examin'd better before he undertook to ſeize Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> and the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> ſince in Prudence and true Policy he ought to have deſtroy'd them quite, or to have diſſembled all.</p>
               <p>So that we may affirm that <hi>Frederick</hi> committed a great fault againſt his own Intereſt, and that Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> ſhow'd, by taking the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s part, that he knew how to reſent the Injuries he had receiv'd like a Man of Sence and Courage.</p>
               <p>But whereas the Queen was at the Head of Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Enemies, and that ſhe abſolutely govern'd <hi>Frederick,</hi> who was eaſy and timorous, ſhe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the firſt motions of her Paſſion. In fine the Earl was too Rich, and had too many Friends, which are Crimes hard to be juſtify'd: And indeed that was the real cauſe of all his Misfortunes, and of thoſe of the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> who is ſtill a Priſoner.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99996:55"/>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:99996:55"/>
            <head>A SUPPLEMENT TO Count ULFELD'S LIFE,</head>
            <head type="sub">The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO I was acquainted many Years ſince with the Truths contain'd in the foregoing cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and uſeful Treatiſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in what relates to the violent and unjuſt Perſecutions and Calumnies rais'd againſt thoſe Heroical Perſons, Count <hi>Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi> and his Lady, mention'd in the ſame, I never put Pen to Paper before, to give the World an account thereof, and perhaps had not done it now, had not the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99996:56"/>accidentally and unexpectedly fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands, by the means of a Perſon with whom I was privately diſcourſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe Tragedies, which made me ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the World was already better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith than I imagin'd. Whereupon baniſhing all Fears, and not valuing the hatred which I am ſonſible Truth creates againſt thoſe who are zealous for it, who are lovers of Juſtice, and who are concern'd for thoſe who are unjuſtly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, defam'd and perſecuted; I thought, fit both for the Glory of God, and for the inſtruction of others, to put the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it being very ſcarce in <hi>French,</hi> as alſo to induce the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, by making a due reflection on the Tranſactions of remote Countries, as well as their own, to be the more grateful to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and to bleſs him for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of living now under a King who is a zealous promoter of Piety and Juſtice, abhorring Oppreſſion and Violence, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing Vice and Baſeneſs, leſt they ſhould provoke God to give them ſuch Rulers as they have already partly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd, and ſuch as are mention'd in the foregoing Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99996:56"/>
            <p>The Additions I now deſign to make to the ſame, will conſiſt in theſe three Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> An Extract of ſome of the main Points of Count <hi>Ulfeld</hi>'s Apology againſt the laſt Calumnies rais'd againſt him, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>French</hi> by himſelf a little before his Death, a Copy whereof is come to my hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Relation of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Proceedings againſt Doctor <hi>Otho Sperling</hi> a dear Friend of the ſaid Count <hi>Ulfeld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A ſhort Account of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Ulfeld</hi>'s being put out of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Copenhaguen:</hi> All which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to accept as kindly as I offer it to you, and to excuſe the plainneſs of my Stile, which I look upon to be moſt ſutable to Truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99996:57"/>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:99996:57"/>
            <head>A SUPPLEMENT TO Count ULFELD's LIFE.</head>
            <p>FIRST, As to the Count's Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy written in <hi>French</hi> by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a little before his Death, and ſent to a particular Friend of his to be perus'd by him, in order to the publiſhing thereof, which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would ſpeedily have been perform'd, had it not been deferr'd by his ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Death mention'd in the foregoing Treatiſe, as well as upon the account of ſome particular Conſiderations relating to the impriſon'd Counteſs and Doctor <hi>Sperling.</hi> The main Heads whereof I ſhall here inſert with all the candor and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99996:58"/>ſincerity imaginable, and in as few words as poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He complains of the illegal Proceedings of his Enemies, contrary to the uſual behaviour of Chriſtians, in condemning him upon pretended Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, without ſummoning, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him to make his defence; nay, which is worſt, for their paſſing a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Condemnation upon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his being acquainted with the ſaid Accuſation: From which he infers as a main argument of his Innocence, that it was a meer contrivance and invention of his Enemies, abſolutely to ruine him and his Family, and as great a Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as thoſe mention'd in the foregoing Treatiſe, of which he was abſolv'd by his Judges; and therefore that his ſaid Enemies foreſeeing the like ſucceſs, and confuſion to themſelves, in caſe he ſhould be allow'd to make his Defence, reſolv'd to go another way to work by force and violence, but ſtill under pretence of ſome groundieſs Accuſations in order as aforeſaid abſolutely to ruine him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that he and his Lady being once deſtroy'd, their Malice and Wickedneſs would be bury'd in Oblivion, and they
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99996:58"/>freed from the publick Cenſures they now lay privately under, and are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of.</p>
            <p>He ſhews withal that their inſatiable Covetouſneſs, and deſire to poſſeſs his and his Lady's vaſt Eſtates, under ſome lawful pretence, had no ſmall ſhare in their ſaid Contrivances and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>To which Reaſons we may add that which is alledg'd by the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s juſt Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Revenge for all their unjuſt and violent Proceedings againſt him; to prevent which they judg'd it neceſſary, to forge the ſaid Calumny, in order to deſtroy him under a ſpecious pretence to blind the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Count proceeds fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to put down and examine the grounds of ſo cruel a Septence, given againſt him and his Family, <hi>viz.</hi> He to be put to a moſt ignominious Death as a Traitor and a Rebel, to forfeit all his Titles, Honours and Eſtate, his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be depriv'd of. Honour and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, baniſh'd out of all the King's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, with other Cruelties menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd in the ſaid Sentence.</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:99996:59"/>
               <head>They ground their ſaid Sentence upon the following Articles.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Upon their having Informations, Advices and original Papers from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of a high Degree and Quality, not to be diſputed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Upon the Count's having acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd his paſt Faults under his own Hand, in order to obtain a Pardon and his Freedom, and his having ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd the King's Mercy by committing new Crimes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Upon the Count's having given a Reverſion under his own Hand and Seal, promiſing never to attempt any thing againſt his Majeſty, or Royal Family, or againſt his State, or to do any thing to his Prejudice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Upon the Count's taking an Oath of Fealty to the King, which he had alſo given under his own Hand.</p>
               <p>This is all they have alledg'd againſt him to prove their Accuſation; which was that he had conſpir'd againſt the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> and his Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deſigning to introduce a new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his Kingdoms, by ſtirring
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99996:59"/>up his Subjects to Rebellion, by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Foreign Princes which they do not name.</p>
               <p>In concluſion they declare, That they did not ſummon the Count to anſwer to the ſaid Accuſations, becauſe it was a Caſe in which no other form of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs was requir'd, which way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding was cuſtomary in many Parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers">
               <head>The Count anſwers the aforeſaid Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles as followeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Informations and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from any Perſons of whatever De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or Quality are not ſufficient prooſs to conclude a Perſon guilty without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Examination; witneſs the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Accuſations formerly made by the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> himſelf againſt the ſaid Count, mention'd in the foregoing Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> of deſigning to poiſon the King, and the ſeveral Crimes laid to his charge at the Court of <hi>Sweden:</hi> which Accuſations tho abſolutely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd to be true by the ſaid King, and Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> and his Lady's being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd Traitors to ſeveral Princes, yet neither the Council in <hi>Denmark,</hi> nor the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> did take for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99996:60"/>but allow'd them a fair Trial, in both which the Count and his Lady were found and declar'd Innocent. All which notwithſtanding, the ſaid King cauſes the ſame Perſon anew to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by his own Servants and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures upon the like weak ground of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Informations, without hearing him in his own defence, and without any probable or apparent Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to confirm the matter: Therefore he deſires to know the neceſſity there was, to precipitate a Sentence in this manner, without allowing him the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time which was neceſſary to make his Defence, and to hear his Reaſons? Were there any Soldiers in the Field at his Devotion? Were any Levies made, even of one Man, againſt him or the State? Can they ſhew or name the leaſt Officer imploy'd in his Service, or under his Pay to ſerve againſt them or the State? Can they prove the leaſt Correſpondence held in the Country, which might really and truly prove the leaſt thing concerning what he is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of? Where are his Accomplices? For it is impoſſible to form ſuch an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe as he is accus'd of, without the aſſiſtance of thoſe of the Country. He
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99996:60"/>is very certain that they can never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce real proofs of a thing that never enter'd in his Mind, which is but a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of the Contrivances and Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſame Cabal which had rais'd the former Calumnies againſt him, which Perſons conceal themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der divers ſhapes for fear of being known. But if Reaſon, Juſtice and a good Cauſe might plead in his defence, he would not fear to appear before the ſevereſt Judges.</p>
               <p>He inlarges more than the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe upon ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, relating to the firſt Calumny about poiſoning the King (of which Trial a particular Treatiſe has been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd in Latin, and in ſeveral other Languages.) Whereby it may appear from ſeveral Paſſages and Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which (ſays the Count) Lomit to relate in this laſt Apology, that ſome very great Perſons have had a hand in it, who may be compar'd to certain Herbs call'd <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> having only us'd <hi>Dina</hi> and <hi>Walter</hi> as Inſtruments; which (ſays he) are the ſame Perſons who have maliciouſly invented this laſt Calumny, tho they have endeavour'd
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99996:61"/>to mask themſelves under the general denomination of other Perſons.</p>
               <p>This is in ſhort what the Count an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the firſt Article of the ground of his Condemnation, with many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements worth the reading; but I am of opinion that what has been ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready is ſufficient to convince the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader of the ſlightneſs of the firſt and main ground of Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a matter of ſuch moment; which way of proceeding without ſummoning or admitting the Parties to make their defence, was never practis'd or approv'd of before among Chriſtians as they ſeem to inſinuate, tho it has been us'd among the <hi>Turks,</hi> eſpecially againſt the richer ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to their ſecond Article grounded upon the Count's Confeſſion, he anſwers, That it was forc'd from him by violence, and threatnings of Death againſt him and his Lady, with ſuch Circumſtances as are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the foregoing Treatiſe, and that Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> at firſt only deſir'd him to write a Petition to demand their Freedom, which the Count wrote willingly in ſuch terms as were moſt proper; but that he refus'd
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99996:61"/>for ſeveral Weeks, as appears by the ſaid Treatiſe, to write any thing like a Confeſſion of Crimes he knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be innocent of.</p>
               <p>In conſideration of which Force and Violence the Count declares the ſaid Ground to be vain and of no force, ſince it is notoriouſly evident, that no Judge is allow'd to receive or make uſe in any Cauſe or Trial, of Writings or Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions extorted from any Perſon whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by any Force or Violence, Fear or Impriſonment, to corroborate or colour any Sentence, but ſuch Declarations and Writings are always rejected as of no force at leaſt among Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to their third Article grounded upon a Reverſion, as they call it, of the Count; he declares likewiſe that it is of no Validity, ſince it was alſo exacted from him before; at leaſt that part of it which they do not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to conceal their wicked Ends in forcing him to make the ſaid Reverſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Count ſhould transfer his whole Eſtate to them, conſiſting of Lands, Jewels and Money, amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a very conſiderable Sum. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Counteſs ſhould renounce her juſt Titles confer'd on her by her Father
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99996:62"/>King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Counteſs of <hi>Sleſwick</hi> and <hi>Holſtein. Item,</hi> To renounce whatever was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted to his advantage in the Treaty of Peace. For as to that part which they mention, he anſwers that it has not been prov'd, nor ever will, that he ever attempted any thing againſt his Majeſty or the Royal Family, ſince the Treaty of Peace concluded between the Crowns of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> in which he was included; and a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Article was inſerted relating to his Perſon and Family, his Friends and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, his Goods Moveables and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveables, and that the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> ſhould reſtore him to the poſſeſſion of all his Eſtate, and make reparation for all Damages; and that both him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and thoſe belonging to him, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſhould have leave to live in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> where they ſhould think fit, in all ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without the leaſt lett, hinderance, or moleſtation: And the ſaid Treaty was ratifi'd anew, and confirm'd by the ſecond and laſt Peace concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Crowns, ſo that they had no reaſon to uſe him ill, for having formerly been forc'd by their Injuſtices
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99996:62"/>and Violences, after five Years patience and ſolicitation, to engage himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, which was the only thing Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> could lay to his charge, when he ask'd him the Reaſons of his and his Lady's Impriſonment; which Queſtion the ſaid <hi>Rantzaw</hi> accounted a new Crime, threatning him with Death in caſe he did perſiſt in diſputing this matter.</p>
               <p>He do's further alledg as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the nullity of the ſaid Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the Promiſe made to him in the ſame had not been perform'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That all his Papers and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which they had ſeiz'd, ſhould be reſtor'd to him without Exception, which was not perform'd; but on the contrary, after they were releas'd out of their Priſon at <hi>Bornholm,</hi> and ſtill carefully guarded by Soldiers, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their having written and ſign'd the ſaid Reverſion, the King caus'd a Trunk full of Letters and Papers of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to be taken from him, out of which he pick'd all thoſe which were of moſt conſequence to them and their Family, which he has never reſtor'd, according to his promiſe inſerted in the ſaid Reverſion.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99996:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſaid Reverſion did contain, that immediately upon the writing and ſigning of the ſame, they ſhould be put at Liberty, but private Orders were given to the Governour to the contrary, for they were ſtill kept under a ſtrong guard of Musketeers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it as well as before: Moreover after their arrival at <hi>Copenhaguen</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd under the ſame Confinement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they had alſo forc'd them to ſign whatever they pleas'd about the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Date and Place of the ſaid Reverſion, as alſo about the Oath of Fealty. It is evident that <hi>pacta ſunt reciproca,</hi> and that the Covenants being broken on one ſide, in Equity the other is no longer oblig'd.</p>
               <p>He thinks it very prepoſterous, that they could perſwade themſelves that a private Perſon as he was could change or alter the leaſt thing contain'd in a publick Treaty of Peace between two Kings. <hi>Item,</hi> That he or his Lady could alienate that which Nature had produc'd and order'd, <hi>viz.</hi> The Titles of Counts and Counteſſes of <hi>Sleſwick</hi> and <hi>Holſtein,</hi> belonging to his Lady and her Poſterity by her Birth, as Daughter
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:99996:63"/>to a great King by a lawful Marriage, as the Author of the ſaid Treatiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, and the Count relates more at large in this Apology; and that hers as well as the King's Father had granted to all his Children of this Marriage, the ſaid Titles and Arms, as it appears by divers Letters from his Chancery, which he caus'd to be written to them on ſeveral occaſions, which Settlements no Monarchs on Earth can reaſonably alter or annul.</p>
               <p>The Count inſiſts largely on the force that has been us'd to compel him to ſign the ſaid Reverſion. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Reſolution the Court had taken to put him and his Lady to Death in caſe of a refuſal, which Count <hi>Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaw</hi> had formerly openly declar'd unto him, and that in a Paſſion too, at a time in which Men commonly ſpeak the truth, which deſign was alſo clearly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough intimated to him by the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The unheard of Cruelties the firſt Governor had us'd towards them, which the Count relates in the ſame manner, as has been declar'd by the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe, but more at
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99996:64"/>large; and he reflects particularly upon that Barbarous and Unchriſtian-like Paſſage, in refuſing to ſend a Miniſter to the Counteſs who was dangerouſly ill, to adminiſter the Sacraments to her, and to comfort her. Which Inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> complaining of to Count <hi>Rantzaw,</hi> when he was ſent to them, thinking it proceeded barely from the Governor's Natural Cruelty, he aſſur'd him that it was done by a particular Order from the Court.</p>
               <p>He inlarges very much upon the ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of the ſaid Reverſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes at laſt, That no Judges hearing the Character of Chriſtians or of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men, could juſtly ground any Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon ſuch forc'd Writings, all the Laws of Chriſtianity being repugnant thereunto, becauſe it is very eaſy for thoſe who have the power and force in hand, to impriſon any Perſon, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to compel him by Violence, Rigour and ill Uſage to ſign any Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever, and to give it the Title of Reverſion, or any other they think moſt proper for their purpoſe.</p>
               <p>He alſo reflects upon their Baſeneſs and Trick to blind the World, by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99996:64"/>them to change the date and place of the ſaid Reverſion when they were brought to <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they were at Liberty, and ſeveral other things which they thought fit to inſert therein: Whereas they were forc'd the firſt time to write it in their hard Priſon at <hi>Burnholm,</hi> and afterwards to write it over again at <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> being ſtill Pris'ners un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſtrong Guard in Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi>'s Houſe, who often pointing to them us'd to tell him, Behold your antient Keepers, who are ready to carry you back to <hi>Bornholm</hi> if you make the leaſt ſcruple to write and ſign what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of you. All which he does pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt before the Eternal God to be true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to the fourth Article on which the Judges ground their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, alledging that ſince he had taken an Oath of Fealty to his Majeſty and to his Royal Family, notwithſtanding which he has ſince conſpir'd both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and his Crown, the ſaid Crime made him guilty of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon both before God and Men.</p>
               <p>To this he anſwers as before, That they can prove no ſuch thing againſt
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99996:65"/>him, and that it is a meer fiction, in order to ruine him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He alledges the Invalidity of the ſaid Writing as well as of the two former, becauſe they were all forc'd from him, when he was a cloſe Pris'ner under a ſtrong Guard, Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> threatning him as aforeſaid, in caſe he made any ſcruple to ſign; adding and proteſting further before God, That he ſign'd the ſaid Papers abſolutely againſt his Will, and without being at liberty, which if he had been, and free to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of himſelf, he would never have ſworn Allegiance to <hi>Frederick,</hi> ſince he had already taken the ſaid Oath to ſerve the Crown of <hi>Sweden,</hi> from which he could not depart to pay Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to any other Prince; which alone would have been ſufficient to hinder him from ſo doing, beſides that he had no reaſon to ſerve a Prince who had kept and us'd him like a Slave, tho he was born Free, and of free Parents. Moreover that Oaths extorted from any Perſons can never be pleaſing to, nor binding before God, but are void of themſelves; neither Divine nor hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws allowing Oaths, Reverſions,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99996:65"/>Bonds, or other obligatory Writings procur'd by force and violence from any Perſons, being under Confinement, or forc'd thereunto againſt their Wills. And if at any tiem any Judg be ſo wicked, and has ſo little Conſcience as to receive and admit ſuch Proofs, and to ground a Sentence thereupon, it is evident that he do's it either out of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Intereſt.</p>
               <p>He do's acknowledg himſelf a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Crown of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and therefore hopes that Crown will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him as a Vaſſal, and upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Article inſerted in the Treaty of Peace in favour of him, which cannot be annihilated by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and by forcing him to renounce the ſame in writing, eſpecially ſince theſe hardſhips are put upon him, as his Enemies pretend, in private, tho not publickly for his having ſerv'd the ſaid Crown.</p>
               <p>This is an Abſtract of what the Count alledges in his own defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their unjuſt and ill-grounded Sentence, which he inlarges with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable things which perhaps might give the Reader more ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99996:66"/>but conſidering the brevity to which we confine our ſelves, this much may ſuffice to ſhew his Innocence and the illegality of the ſaid Sentence.</p>
               <p>Towards the Concluſion he examines and bewails the Hardſhips and Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances put upon his dear Lady, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being any ways guilty, and how ill ſhe was us'd and rewarded in <hi>England</hi> by a Party whom out of Tenderneſs and Compaſſion they had aſſiſted with Money and Jewels in the time of their Diſtreſs and Neceſſity. When Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ifeld</hi> was ſolicitous with Count <hi>Rantzaw</hi> in his Priſon, to know the reaſon why they were robb'd and treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo barbarouſly, deſiring to be brought to a publick Trial to be judg'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of the Kingdom, he only anſwer'd with another Queſtion, asking him whether he did not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that he had ſerv'd the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> in the laſt Wars? To which he gave him an immediate Anſwer which would have ſatisfy'd an impartial Man. But when he deſir'd to know what his Lady had done to be treated with the ſame rigour, and robb'd of all her Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Money, Goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ſaid <hi>Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaw</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:99996:66"/>being at a loſs, reply'd in great Paſſion, that in caſe he did continue to criticize and to diſpute thus, he would aſſure them that his buſineſs would be ſoon done, threatning him again with Death: By which it appears that they could lay nothing to her Charge, and that ſhe only ſuffer'd upon her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's account; how juſtly let others judg. He proceeds further to ſatisfy the World, how ill he is rewarded for the great Service he did the King in cauſing him to be elected, which Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he relates at large in the ſame manner as it is mention'd in his Life; how he alone ſtood up for him againſt a powerful Party, and maintain'd that they ought to elect him, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the reaſons they urg'd for his Excluſion, inſomuch that he was the chief inſtrument to raiſe him to the Throne; moreover that he was the firſt Perſon that brought him the publick News thereof in the Name of the two Kingdoms, and gave him the Titles of King and Majeſty, as alſo that he plac'd the Crown upon his Head with the Biſhops before the Altar of the Cathedral Church at <hi>Copenhaguen.</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:99996:67"/>He adds that he may freely and ſafely affirm, That had it not been for him, <hi>Frederick</hi> had never been King, which he can prove with ſuch manifeſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that were the King acquainted therewith, he would be amaz'd at what paſs'd at his Election, and that it wanted but little that another was not elected in his Place.</p>
               <p>Before I make an end of what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi>'s Perſon, it will be proper to inſtance one Paſſage, by which it will appear that his Enemies hatred and animoſities againſt him, were not extinguiſh'd even by his Death. They ſent ſeveral Perſons in ſearch of his Grave, in order to unbury him and to triumph over his Body, as they had already done over his Effigies at <hi>Copenhaguen:</hi> But their Emiſſaries were ſo narrowly watch'd by the poor Count's Sons, that few of them came back to give an account of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, inſomuch that at laſt they were diſcourag'd from ſending any more, beſides that they found it was impoſſible to find him out; for as ſoon as he died upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of his Life relates, the Perſons to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99996:67"/>whom he did commit the care of his Body, bury'd him in the neareſt landing Place, which his Sons being acquainted with, they repair'd thither with ſpeed, foreſeeing their Enemies would ſend in ſearch of him, and deſir'd the Biſhop of the place to cauſe him to be remov'd, by reaſon that being a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> it was not fit he ſhould lie among <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> that place being only appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſuch; upon which account this requeſt was granted, and they together with their Father's antient and faithful Servants, being arm'd, remov'd him on Horſeback, and bury'd him in a place not publickly known, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deceiv'd the expectation of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. They alſo expected to have found their Father's remaining Treaſure conſiſting of Jewels ſew'd up in his Buff-Coat, but he was rifl'd before their Arrival, and they could never receive the leaſt ſatisfaction about it, but were oblig'd to content themſelves with the bare Buff-Coat, and with the loſs of the Jewels, as well as of their paternal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Some Papers were found about him written in Ciphers, which one of his Sons thought might be about ſome
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99996:68"/>Secret he had often told him he would communicate to him before his Death; which he fancy'd might be relating to the Philoſopher's Stone about the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation or rather ſeparation of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, the rather becauſe he found he had a Furnace in a private Chamber, where no Body was admitted, and that notwithſtanding the vaſt Sums his Enemies had taken from him, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in want, but provided very handſomly for his Children abroad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the ſecond part of this Supplement relating to Doctor <hi>Otho Sperling,</hi> who deſcended from a good Family at <hi>Hamburg,</hi> fam'd parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly for Men of Parts and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Learning:</p>
               <p>He marry'd a Lady of the Noble Family of the <hi>Schwendys,</hi> deſcended from the great General and Stateſman, <hi>Lazarus Schwendy,</hi> ſo much celebrated in Hiſtory, eſpecially in that of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> in whom it may be ſaid that <hi>Mars</hi> and the Muſes had made a ſtrict alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he being beſides his Martial Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments a perſon of eminent Learning, as it partly appears by his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99996:68"/>writings as yet extant, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by his Epiſtles <hi>ad Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and others.</p>
               <p>This great Vertue and Learning of his Anceſtors on both ſides, Dr. <hi>Sperling</hi> did endeavour to imitate, in which he prov'd very ſucceſsful, and was one of the moſt learned Men of his Age, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in Phyſick and the ſtudy of Nature, about which he held Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencies in ſeveral parts. Moreover he was a Man of extraordinary Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Vertue, of admirable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, ſweet and agreeable in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which Qualities gain'd him the hearts of all vertuous Perſons, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly that of Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> whom he became acquainted with in his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, (which were very conſiderable in ſeveral parts) and by degrees did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the ſtricteſt Friendſhip with him that could be expected from two Hearts equally addicted to Vertue and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg. The Count was ſo much taken with his eminent Qualities and great Underſtanding, that he took him for his Companion in ſeveral Embaſſies, and particularly into <hi>England,</hi> in King <hi>Charles</hi> the I's time, to whom the ſaid
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99996:69"/>Count brought Ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the behalf of the King his Maſter; at which time theſe two Perſons were brought into an eminent danger and had an extraordinary Deliverance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken and impriſon'd by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarians, who paſs'd a Sentence of Death upon them as Friends to their Enemy, for which they had prepar'd themſelves with great Courage againſt the next Morning, when unexpectedly and by a ſingular Providence the King's Party attack'd them in the Night, took the Houſe in which they were kept Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and reſcu'd them.</p>
               <p>This great familiarity and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between the Count and Dr. <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> involv'd the laſt in the unjuſt Perſecutions of the other; being tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by wicked Men, who natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have an antipathy to Vertue; ſuch as Fortune by God's permiſſion raiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Children to try their Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. This theſe two worthy Perſons, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Counteſs <hi>Eleonora,</hi> did ſufficiently experience, and therefore the Count's Enemies never fail'd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve Dr. <hi>Sperling</hi> in all his Concerns, and in all the Calumnies they rais'd
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:99996:69"/>againſt him. So that in the firſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny about poiſoning the King, they accus'd him of having provided the Poiſon, as being then the King's Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, of which Calumny he was then as well as the Count publickly clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Accuſers puniſh'd, as it is related in the foregoing Treatiſe. And tho he was not mention'd in the laſt Calumny and Sentence of Treaſon publiſh'd againſt the Count, yet his Enemies in order to juſtify their Treachery and Baſeneſs, prevail'd with the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to accuſe him of having kept a Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Count. In fine, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were firmly reſolv'd utterly to deſtroy the Count, and had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd the innocent Counteſs, the only remaining Perſon they were jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of, and whom they thought capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to oppoſe their wicked Deſigns, by aſſiſting the Count with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and to diſcover their Villany, was Dr. <hi>Sperling.</hi> For which reaſon, they put their Heads together to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how to ſecure and ruine him and his Family; but whereas they were
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:99996:70"/>ſenſible that they could not obtain their End by the means of Juſtice, they were oblig'd to have recourſe to Tricks and Treachery, the ſame means they had us'd before towards the Count and Counteſs, his Friends.</p>
               <p>In order hereunto they ſuborn'd a Villain and Traitor, one <hi>Hagedorn,</hi> who put their Project in execution <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> like, in the manner following. He came to the Doctor as a Stranger, pretending to have a ſingular Reſpect and Eſteem for his great skill in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and deſir'd him to viſit and give his Advice to a certain Friend of his, whom he pretended to be ill of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Diſeaſe. This good Man dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Surprize went along with him in a Coach to viſit his ſaid Patient: On their return, coming by a certain place where the ſaid <hi>Hagedorn</hi> had plac'd another Ruffian like himſelf, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to meet him accidentally, he told the Doctor pointing to him, That that Gentleman had been a great Traveller in the <hi>Indies</hi> and other remote Parts, and that he had an extraordinary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of many curious things, asking him, Whether he would allow him to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:99996:70"/>take him into the Coach. Dr. <hi>Sperling,</hi> who he knew delighted to diſcourſe with Perſons of that Character, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſented thereunto. Soon after his coming into the Coach they drew up the Glaſſes, the Weather being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rainy and windy; whereupon he perceiv'd that he was betray'd and a Pris'ner, and he endeavouring to call People to his aſſiſtance, tho in vain, by reaſon of the ſwiftneſs of the motion and the great noiſe the Coach and the Wind made, they gagg'd him, in ſo much that he was half choak'd, and in this manner carry'd him to <hi>Gluckſtat,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Copenhaguen.</hi> In the mean time the good City of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> where Dr. <hi>Sperling</hi> was very much belov'd, to ſhew their abhorrence of this Villanous Action, caus'd the Bell of Infamy to be rung, to give all the People notice thereof, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter the ſaid <hi>Hagedorn</hi> in their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Book as a Traitor. After this the Doctor's Effects in <hi>Denmark</hi> (which were very conſiderable) were all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated without any cauſe, and part thereof given to the ſaid <hi>Hagedorn</hi> as a Reward for his Treachery.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:99996:71"/>
               <p>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was graciouſly pleas'd to take Dr. <hi>Sperling</hi>'s part, he being his Subject and under his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as a Member of the Chapter of <hi>Hamburg,</hi> and did highly reſent and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of this illegal Action, as well to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as to other Princes, and particularly to the King of <hi>England</hi> who was <hi>Guarantée</hi> of the Treaty of Peace between the two Northern Crowns: And in anſwer to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Letter to him, did reſute the weak grounds on which the ſaid King endeavour'd to juſtify the ſaid Action; one of which was, That Doctor <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> had formerly been in his Service as his Phyſitian, and pretending that he ſtill was ſo, becauſe he had not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd up his Commiſſion; anſwering, That his Letter of Demiſſion (which he had obtain'd on honourable Terms, at his Requeſt, after the Trial of the poiſoning buſineſs) was a ſufficient Diſcharge from any farther obligation or ſubjection to the King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> ſo that the caſe was not what he had been, but under whoſe Soveraignty, Juriſdiction and Protection he was when he was carry'd away from
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:99996:71"/>
                  <hi>Hamburg,</hi> which is a free Imperial City: in which caſe the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> was oblig'd to act according to <hi>Jus Gentium,</hi> to the end that the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of the Empire, and the <hi>Jus Superioritatis</hi> of the Dutchy of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> to which the Chapter of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> does belong, might not be violated. And that ſince he found by the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Letter that the greateſt and only Crime laid to Doctor <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>'s Charge, was his having kept a ſecret Correſpondence above all others with Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> he deſir'd on that account to have a particular and exact relation of all the particulars of the Crimes imputed to both, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which he could not paſs a true Judgment on the nature of this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Correſpondence laid to Doctor <hi>Sperling</hi>'s Charge. He concludes with this conſidence, that the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> will be pleas'd to ſuſpend all farther Proceedings againſt the ſaid Doctor, and to conſider his Majeſty's Reaſons in both his Letters, and to put the Doctor at Liberty again, and ſend him back into that part of the Empire from whence he was taken, his Majeſty
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:99996:72"/>promiſing upon his Royal Word, That in caſe any one has any thing to urge againſt the ſaid Doctor, and ſhall propoſe it <hi>in competenti foro,</hi> he will cauſe Juſtice to be adminiſtred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to any Perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> receiv'd no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to this Letter (of which I have a Copy by me, from which I have taken this Abſtract.) Doctor <hi>Sperling</hi> remain'd ſtill a cloſe Priſoner, neither was the matter of Fact, of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Crimes alledg'd againſt him and Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> clearly and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially communicated to him, that his Majeſty might be able to judg of it; the <hi>Danes</hi> dreading the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion they had formerly drawn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves, when they accus'd the ſaid Count at the Court of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as it is related in the foregoing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: which way of proceeding may chance at ſome time or other to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a War between the two Crowns, when his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> (who was then a Minor, and who is a pious Prince, loving Juſtice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Oppreſſion) comes to inſpect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:99996:72"/>the ſaid Matter, not only becauſe Doctor <hi>Sperling</hi> as well as Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi> were under his Protection, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe, as I am credibly inform'd, a particular Agreement was made between the two Crowns, That in caſe any Nobleman of <hi>Denmark</hi> has a juſt Exception to make to the ſaid King's Sentence againſt him, he may appeal to the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Sperling</hi>'s Children finding no Redreſs by their Applications in <hi>Sweden</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of the ſecret Intrigues of the Court of <hi>Denmark,</hi> preſented moſt humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to <hi>Frederick,</hi> and after his Death to the preſent King <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and alſo made uſe of the Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſeveral other Perſons of Note: but nothing could prevail while the late Queen Mother to the preſent King was alive, as probably it might have done for him as well as for the Counteſs of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas'd ſoon after her Death, which affords no ſmall ſcope of Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I leave to the ingenious Reader's Conſideration.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:99996:73"/>
               <p>Thus this good and innocent Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was forc'd to end his Days in a Priſon, after Seventeen Years impriſonment, which he bore with great Courage and Patience like a Chriſtian Soldier triumphing over his Enemies, when they thought they had vanquiſh'd him. He died in the Eightieth Year of his Age, having ſpent the time of his Confinement as well as his former Days in Study and Contemplation; and he told a Friend of his in a Letter, That he had receiv'd greater Illuminations in Natural things, during his ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, than while he liv'd in the World: I have alſo ſeen a Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of his written in Cyphers, which he left to his ſaid Friend, which I partly know to be a piece of great moment.</p>
               <p>During all the time of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and many Years after it, his eldeſt Son, who is a Doctor in Law, and a Man of univerſal Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, liv'd with his Siſters at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> very handſomly upon the Means that were left them, (which their Enemies had not been able to reach)
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:99996:73"/>even beyond what could be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Perſons under their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Affliction, having ſuffer'd ſo great a Loſs, and being depriv'd of a Head ſo capable to improve their Eſtate, till at laſt ſome difference oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring between him and the Senate of <hi>Hamburg,</hi> on the account of ſome words he had utter'd out of zeal to a Client of his abroad, in a Cauſe he had depending before the ſaid Senate; which being diſpleaſed thereat, confin'd and fin'd him: which Affront being high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſented by him, he reſolv'd to ſecure himſelf from receiving the like for the future; in order whereunto he thought fit to implore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of ſome Prince, able to keep them in awe, and not having the ſame intereſt or acquaintance in <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> (to which King it ſeem'd moſt reaſonable he ſhould make his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication as being his Father's So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign) as he had in <hi>Denmark,</hi> where he had been formerly about his Father's Affairs, he apply'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to that Court, where by the means and intereſt of an old Acquaintance of his, a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Miniſter, and a great
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99996:74"/>Politician, he obtain'd the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Character of Counſellor to this preſent King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> under which Character he continu'd ſome Years at <hi>Hamburg</hi> without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, till at laſt having made greater intereſt yet with the ſaid King, he reſolv'd to live at <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> where he is alſo Profeſſor of Greek, and of Hiſtory, in which he does excel and has few Equals, as well as in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and in the knowledg of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals.</p>
               <p>Thus much in relation to Dr. <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> may ſuffice at preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to the third intended part of this Treatiſe relating to the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd Counteſs of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> I ſhall acquaint you in few words, that ſoon after the late Queen Mother's Death ſhe was releas'd out of her Priſon at <hi>Copenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen,</hi> but is ſtill confin'd in the Iſle of <hi>Laland,</hi> where ſhe muſt be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to live upon a ſmall Revenue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the vaſt Eſtate that has been violently taken from her and hers.</p>
               <p>This great Heroin, Daughter of a great King, by a lawful Marriage, may
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:99996:74"/>juſtly be admir'd, and ſerve as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the World for her Courage and Conſtancy amidſt the greateſt of Afflictions and Perſecutions, having beſides her firſt barbarous Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſeventeen Months undergone another at leaſt of twenty four Years continuance at <hi>Copenhaguen:</hi> which may move the Compaſſion of all good Chriſtians, and particularly of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, to aſſiſt her and the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Dr. <hi>Sperling,</hi> ſome of which have never engag'd themſelves in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> The Counteſs has out-liv'd her greateſt Enemies, which ſhe could never have done had ſhe not had a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit above the common reach, and a knowledg ſuperiour to moſt of her Sex. I have ſpoken with ſome, who have ſeen her ſince her being put at liberty, who do ſtrangely admire her great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Contempt of the World. <hi>Sic</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Stat virtus repulſae neſcia ſordidae</l>
                     <l>Intaminatis fulget honoribus.</l>
                     <l>Nec ſumit aut ponit ſecures</l>
                     <l>Arbitrio popularis aurae.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
